<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/4.1.6" created="2016-03-06 19:29" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Crossing the Rubikhan</title>
	<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com</link>
	<description>&#34;Alea Yakta Est&#34;</description>
	<pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2016 19:29:01 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://crossingtherubikhan.com</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>http://crossingtherubikhan.com</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>2</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>buzkashi</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>cooperthomascooper@gmail.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Cooper Thomas]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Cooper]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Thomas]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>4</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>jenkinsb12</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>jenkinsb12@gmail.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Benjie Jenkins]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Benjie]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Jenkins]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>


	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=4.1.6</generator>

	<item>
		<title>Blah</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=476</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 23:23:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=476</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[test test test]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>476</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-10-23 18:23:53</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-10-23 23:23:53</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>blah</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>draft</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Hello There!</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/hello-there/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 19:42:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jenkinsb12]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=483</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Thanks for visiting our blog. We'll be using this space to keep everyone informed on how our preparations are progressing, and of course how the drive is going once the rally actually begins. But that's still pretty far off; for now, we need to deal with some basic necessities. Like a car! If you'd like to help us out in that department, head on down to the "Get Involved" section of the website, where you can conveniently donate through PayPal. Remember that the majority of your donation will go to help keep the earth cool and shelter orphaned children, two causes I think we can all agree are very worthwhile. So please consider supporting us!

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>483</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-10-25 14:42:14</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-10-25 19:42:14</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>hello-there</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[4]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Cars and Carbon Consciousness</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/cars-and-carbon-consciousness/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 06:20:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=657</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Greetings, good readers, and welcome to the first (well, second) installment in our ongoing Mongol Rally chronicles! Although our July 19th start date is still several months away, we are already in the midst of planning. And by that, we really just mean ogling photo essays of Mongolia, practicing throat singing, and getting a head start on the obligatory Mongol Rally muttonchops (not really). We'll do our very best to keep you abreast of our planning efforts as we continue to prepare for the 10,000-mile adventure that lies ahead.

This post addresses a question that a number of you have raised, and one that we believe merits a blog entry of its own:

<em>“Isn’t driving 10,000 miles sort of antithetical to the Cool Earth Foundation’s whole ‘save the rainforest and reduce greenhouse gases’ mission?”</em>

Our answer? On paper, yes – driving 10,000 miles is not good for the environment, and we won't pretend like it is. In reality, however, the emissions we will produce over the course of our journey pale in comparison to the emissions we’ll <em>prevent </em>from entering the atmosphere by donating to Cool Earth. Bear with me, as I attempt to illustrate this comparison using real figures:

According to Cool Earth, <em>£60</em> – a hair under $100USD, at the time of writing – protects <em>one acre of rainforest</em>. So, if we donate <em>$1,500</em> to Cool Earth (that's half of our total fundraising amount, with the other half going to SOS Children's Villages), we’ll presumably protect <em>15 acres</em> of rainforest.

Now, clearing <em>one acre</em> of rainforest emits <em>260 tonnes of CO2</em> into the atmosphere. (Of course, it also displaces countless monkeys, tapirs, and anacondas). So, if we can protect <em>15 acres</em> of forest, we’ll effectively keep <em>3,900 tonnes of CO2</em> safely out of the atmosphere. Meanwhile, those trees on the ground will continue to belch out the oxygen we so dearly need, while the monkeys inhabiting them will go about their daily mischief-making uninterrupted.

Moving along, consider that <em>260 tonnes of CO2</em> – again, the amount produced by <em>one acre</em> of deforestation – is roughly equivalent to driving an average petrol-powered vehicle around the globe...a staggering <em>32 times</em>! And the <em>3,900 tonnes</em> of CO2 that our donation will help keep out of the atmosphere? That equals something like <em>480 laps around the planet!</em> See where I'm going with this?

If these numbers are correct, then <em>one planetary lap</em> produces something like <em>8.125 tonnes of CO2</em>. We’re driving approximately <em>10,000 miles</em>, or a little less than halfway around the planet. So while we’re certainly guilty of producing our own greenhouse gases – approximately <em>3.26 tonnes</em>, if we assume that the circumference of the planet is <em>24,901</em> <em>miles</em> (as our good friend Google seems to indicate) and that our odometer hits the <em>10,000 mark</em> – WE ARE STILL KEEPING AROUND <em>3,896 tonnes of CO2 </em>SAFELY OUT OF THE ATMOSPHERE! And that, I think, is something we can all be proud of.

So, as these hasty calculations hopefully illustrate, our little jaunt to Mongolia isn't quite so environmentally harmful as it may initially seem, in the grand scheme of things.
<p style="text-align: center;">*          *          *</p>
In other news, today we hit our charity fundraising goal of $3,000 – hooray! While this is an exciting milestone, however, we still need your support in order to make this trip a reality. So, if you've got any coins rattling around in your pockets (err, Paypal account), or just want to help four young lads realize a dream, head on over to our <a title="donation page" href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate" target="_blank">donation page</a>. The rewards packages we've prepared for you – not to mention our forthcoming updates from the road – will ensure that you won't regret it. If anything, do it for the monkeys and the tapirs!

And of course, stay tuned for more blog posts in the near future.

//Cooper]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>657</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-12-17 01:20:30</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-12-17 06:20:30</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>cars-and-carbon-consciousness</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[cars-and-carbon-consciousness-justifying-our-drive]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Happy New Year!</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/happy-new-year/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 21:15:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=775</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[It's 2014 in Mongolia!

Beloved friends, family, and people who read obscure blogs for fun: I wanted to take a few minutes to update you on our preparations—at least those outside of calculating carbon footprints and monkey mischief quotients. In the midst of our holiday break, Cooper, Benjie, Keshav, and I have struck a delicate balance between Rally preparations, sleeping, and catching up on Homeland.

On top of finding generous sponsors and watching Cooper build us a beautiful interactive map, we’ve allowed ourselves to dive into the nitty gritty of day to day equipment needs (sample: 4 headlamps, 2 walkie talkies, 1 car).

We’ve nailed down the hilariously bureaucratic means through which we will secure our visas. I’ll double check with Keshav but I think Turkmenistan requires $40 cash and a floral offering from the eldest member of our village.

We’ve reached out for advice wherever we can get it. Thanks to everyone for the invaluable recommendations regarding everything from bribes to brakepads. A couple of favorite pieces of advice have been to chat up that locals as much as we can and to politely refuse offerings of snuff by sniffing it and finding a way to adequately pantomime ‘no thank you.’

We have our work cut out for us with seven months until we launch in London. Our biggest tasks include acquiring a car, learning how to drive it, and learning how to fix it. Piece of cake, right?

Before I sign off, I want to say a huge thanks to all who have donated! We cannot properly express just how much it means that you’re supporting our causes as well as our dream of adventure. Also, shout out to <a href="http://bigfrog.com/pdx" title="Big Frog Custom T-Shirts" target="_blank">Big Frog Custom T-Shirts</a> in Portland for printing up some great looking t-shirts (look out for ‘em on campus this winter!).

 And if you’re feeling in the holiday spirit and want to fund a fan belt or our passage across the Caspian, I encourage you to visit our <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate" title="Donations Page" target="_blank">donations page</a> and check out the wonderfully weird rewards packages we’ll give you in return.

 Hobey Ho, let’s go!

 //Nick]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>775</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-12-31 16:15:07</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-12-31 21:15:07</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>happy-new-year</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>A Culture a Day...</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/a-culture-a-day/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 20:33:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=819</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Hello Friends!

We’re pumped to announce our new partnership with <a href="http://www.tripwing.com" title="TripWing" target="_blank">TripWing</a>—a travel itinerary booking website that books entire tours along with the standard flight and hotel reservations. While they probably can’t help us pitch a tent in the Turkmen desert, they can do pretty much everything else travel related. Check out everything TripWing can do by visiting their <a href="http://www.tripwing.com" title="website" target="_blank">website</a>. Oh yeah, and feel free to check out our <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate" title="donations page" target="_blank">donations page</a> too….

Until next time, here’s a list of weird cultural idiosyncrasies we’re likely to encounter on our drive: 

<p text align=center><strong>Obscure Customs We’ll Inevitably Break Along the Way</strong></p>

<strong>Turkey:</strong> Holding your thumb between your index and middle finger is the equivalent of flipping the bird and to be avoided at all costs. While not verified by any reputable source, this likely stems from too many lost noses in the “Got Your Nose!” disaster of 1963.

<strong>Azerbaijan:</strong> If you meet a person with empty buckets, you are bound for misfortune. Cast down your bucket where you are!

<strong>Uzbekistan:</strong> Refilling a guest’s teacup that is more than half-full is a rude way of saying that you want them to leave. After three smelly weeks packed into a tiny car, this technique may be abetted by good old-fashioned passive aggression.

<strong>Georgia:</strong> Bring an odd number of flowers, as even numbers are used in funerals. This means that when Benjie buys a dozen roses from the Tbilisi florist, he can give 11 to his crush and still have one left over for his ego.

<strong>Kyrgyzstan:</strong> If a bottle of vodka is opened, it must be finished in one sitting. Good luck, Keshav.

<strong>Kazakhstan:</strong> A boiled sheep’s head is sometimes presented on a beautiful plate to the most honored guest, who then symbolically serves sections of the head among the guests. The daughter-in-law and host’s daughter are given sections of the tongue as a reminder to ‘hold their tongues.’ Cooper will presumably be given the teeth as a reminder to brush his teeth.

<strong>Russia:</strong> Do not bring yellow flowers; it is a sign of cheating on love. I don’t know why these etiquette websites are so obsessed with flowers.

<strong>Uzbekistan:</strong> Partially because unemployment is rampant, people generally have a lot of free time. There is no set bus schedule: buses generally just run whenever they fill up/feel like it. Translation: if our car breaks down in Uzbekistan, we'd better not be in a hurry.

<strong>Mongolia:</strong> If you accidentally tap someone’s foot with your own, immediately shake hands with him. Since Mongolia is the most sparsely populated country in the world, I can’t imagine this has ever happened.

<strong>Turkmenistan:</strong> Narrowly beating out Justin Bieber as the most bizarre cult of personality this side of North Korea, Turkmenistan’s former President For Life, Saparmurat Niyazov is one crazy individual. He renamed himself Turkmenbashi, meaning “Father of all Turkmen” and subsequently renamed several cities, towns, streets, and the month of January after himself. There is a 50ft tall golden statue of him in the capital that rotates so as to always face the sun. While Turkmenbashi died in 2006, a book promulgating his glory,written by none other than Turkmenbashi himself, is still taught in all Turkmen schools. My guess would be to avoid making fun of this dude until we hit the Uzbek border.

<3
Nick]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>819</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-02-04 15:33:10</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-02-04 20:33:10</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>a-culture-a-day</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Captain&#039;s Log: February Doldrums Lead to March Madness</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/captains-log-february-doldrums-lead-to-march-madness/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 18:43:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=853</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[What’s up RubikhanArtists?

The weather remains unforgivably cold in Hanover (negative 8°F next week? In March?) and Team Crossing the Rubikhan is dreaming of 96-degree days on the M37 highway between Turkmenbashi and Ashgabat. While waiting to receive our second passports—just in case the rogue border patrolman is less than pumped about the two Israeli stamps I have on page 7—we’ve begun to prepare the rest of our applications for visas.

For those of you who are unfamiliar with the process, applying for one visa can be a bureaucratic nightmare. We need six each—and that includes Russia: The Visa To End All Visas. This means we need to confirm hostel bookings, procure our international driver's licenses, fill out mounds of paperwork, and somehow convince a series of questionably run government agencies that driving a beat up old car from the UK to Mongolia is a perfectly legitimate and not-at-all-sketchy reason to gain ingress into their esteemed nation.

Cooper is going bald trying to keep the rest of us on top of our responsibilities while other serious obligations like schoolwork and Sporcle fight for our extremely limited attention (thanks, technology!). The team is hoping for a miracle tomorrow when the four of us make the quick jaunt to Montpelier to get our international driver’s licenses. There have been murmurs from Benjie that preparing for a certain fraternity formal may get in the way. We get it, Benjie—you have a hot date. You're still coming. Pics to follow (of the Montpelier trip, not of Benjie’s hot date). Maybe this will be the first installment of <a href="http://tripwing.com" title="Tripwing's" target="_blank">Tripwing’s</a> highly anticipated #SideMirrorSaturday?

That’s all we’ve got for now. Like always, thanks a ton to all of our incredible donors and sponsors! Special shout-out to <a href="http://www.goalzero.com/" title="GoalZero" target="_blank">GoalZero</a> for sending us some amazing solar-powered gear. 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/DSC_0004-1024x680.jpg">

<p align= "center"><img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/DSC_0001-3.jpg"></p>

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/DSC_0009-1024x680.jpg">

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/DSC_0014-1024x680.jpg">

<p align="center">Bonus: check out the video of our grand (box) opening below!
<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/87243507?byline=0&amp;color=0097fb" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>

Also, hello to all the <a href="http://tripwing.com/" title="Tripwingers" target="_blank">Tripwingers</a> out there! If you feel like throwing us a bone, take a gander at our <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/donate/" title="ridiculous rewards packages" target="_blank">ridiculous rewards packages</a> and perhaps even donate a shekel or three <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/donate/" title="here" target="_blank">here</a>!

Until next time!

Nick and Team Crossing the Rubikhan
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>853</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-02-28 13:43:54</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-02-28 18:43:54</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>captains-log-february-doldrums-lead-to-march-madness</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The 2014 Montpelier Rally</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/the-2014-montpelier-rally/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 19:19:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=882</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Misalots’i, dzvirp’aso megobrebo! (That’s Georgian for “greetings, dear friends”...but you probably knew that already.) 

On Saturday, three-fourths of Team Crossing the Rubikhan ventured to the alien hamlet of Montpelier, Vermont – typically written in the Latin script as Montpelier, Vermont – in pursuit of adventure, camaraderie, and international driver’s permits. A mini-rally of sorts, this day-long excursion offered Nick, Shav, and Cooper a brief taste of the long hours of driving that await them this summer.

As is common with adventures of this magnitude (Jason’s quest for the golden fleece springs to mind), we encountered a few potentially catastrophic trials along the way. First, we drove to a defunct AAA office, which looked suspiciously like a meth lab. Then, we somehow managed to get lost, despite the presence of three GPS devices in the car. Once we found the real AAA office, poor left-handed Nick had to fill out an entire page of paperwork without smearing the ink. And finally, we nearly lost Shav to a powerful gust of wind. The fact that we overcame all of these obstacles in order to complete our mission-critical objectives surely testifies to our preparedness for the Mongol Rally. 

To reward ourselves for our hard labor, the three of us treated ourselves to <s>several gallons of</s> some delicious artisanal beer from the <a href="http://www.craftbeer.com/news/brewery-news/hill-farmstead-brewery-named-best-brewery-in-the-world-2013" title="Hill Farmstead Brewery Named Best Brewery in the World 2013" target="_blank">highly acclaimed Hill Farmstead Brewery</a>. Unfortunately, the company was unwilling to sponsor us through an in-kind donation...but in all fairness, they’re probably not quite ready to expand into the Uzbek market yet. In due time. Anyway, here are a few of photos from the excursion:

<p text align="center">Nick shows off his sweet new <s>modeling headshots</s> passport photos...
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0024.jpg">

<p text align="center">...before meekly surrendering to the tyrannical left-to-right writing system of the English language.
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0026.jpg">

<p text align="center">Nick and Shav flaunt their hard-earned credentials. Fortunately, there was no driving test, which Shav indubitably would have failed.
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0041.jpg">

<p text align="center">We weren’t kidding about #sidemirrorsaturday. It’s a thing now. Twitter, take notice.
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0031.jpg">

<p text align="center">Nick nervously pilots us along a dirt road. (He was mostly concerned about getting dirt on his car.)
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0051.jpg">

<p text align="center">Shav and Cooper put on their best beer faces.
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0047.jpg">


Did you notice Cooper’s super-limited-edition Crossing the Rubikhan t-shirt, courtesy of our friends at <a href="http://www.bigfrog.com/" title="Big Frog" target="_blank">Big Frog</a>? It’s pretty sweet, right? Well, if you’d like to purchase one for yourself, now you can! Just holler at us – we have them in a range of sizes, and one shirt’ll set you back just $15. We can take Venmo (preferred), cash (also pretty good), Paypal (good), checks (less good) or 14W meal swipes. 

Stay tuned for more updates in the near future. 

//Cooper and Team Crossing the Rubikhan]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>882</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-03-04 14:19:35</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-03-04 19:19:35</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>the-2014-montpelier-rally</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>A Dispatch from Paperwork Purgatory</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/dispatch-paperwork-purgatory/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2014 19:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=918</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<em>“[Paperwork] destroys memory and weakens the mind, relieving it of…work that makes it strong. [Paperwork] is an inhuman thing.”</em>

<em></em>—Socrates

Some people claim that paperwork can be fun. But this week, we (the Rubikhans) collectively decided that these people are either liars, idiots, or soulless drones. Seeking an escape from our daunting academic responsibilities—final examinations were this week—we woke up at the crack of dawn (read: noon) a few days ago to fill out the visa applications that have been hanging over our heads for the past few months. Naturally, this process—which we naively expected to take just a couple of hours—dragged into an agonizingly tedious weeklong activity, and one that we’ll be happy to forget.

See, as American citizens, we need visas for Turkey, Azerbaijan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, Kazakhstan, and Russia (the Big Six). Fortunately, the ’Stans offer a great "buy four, get one free” visa deal, maybe inspired by Domino’s Pizza’s hugely successful Five Five Five marketing campaign, so Kyrgyzstan was exempted from our list. (Kidding.) Unfortunately, however, most of of these countries require proof of travel insurance, proof of sufficient funds, proof of accommodation, and proof of existence. So, we hastily made a few fake hotel bookings (all at five-star resorts, of course), procured some budget insurance, scratched out a couple of letters with our names signed in blood, and then dove headfirst into the mountain of paperwork itself.

<img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-919" alt="RussiaVisa" src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/RussiaVisa-1024x544.png" width="960" height="510" />

And what a mountain it was. As we slogged through tens of impossibly formatted pages and dozens of unintelligible questions, like “direction of activity of organization” (north?), “location of border” (uh, the border?), and “have you ever visited other countries in the past ten years?", our mid-morning gumption deteriorated into mid-afternoon frustration. Even Google Maps seemed determined to thwart our progress, telling us to fly from Tashkent to Bishkek, rather than driving.

<img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-920" alt="googleMaps" src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/googleMaps-1024x556.png" width="960" height="521" />

Finally, after four long, hand-cramping hours of paperwork, our work was done. We stacked up all of our applications, passports, international driver’s permits, personal letters, photos, and booking “confirmations", and dropped them in the mail, along with a hope and a prayer that our passports would come back to us with six beautiful visa stickers – or even at all.

<img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-921" alt="IMG_2783" src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/IMG_2783-1024x701.jpg" width="960" height="657" />

Now, fast forward some 48 hours. On the first day of exams, we all awoke to a dishearteningly lengthy email from the visa processing company informing us that our applications were missing certain documents, that we had answered some questions incorrectly, and that we were getting dangerously close to the Turkmenistan visa application deadline. Naturally, our hearts sank. Determined to finish this daunting task before parting ways for spring break, however, we grudgingly reprinted blank forms, re-answered questions, re-wrote letters, re-scanned the completed documents, and repackaged them for delivery.

With a bit of luck, our applications will actually go through this time around. And if not, we’ll just have to figure out an alternate route that bypasses all official border crossings. That shouldn’t be a problem, right?

//Nick, Cooper and Benjie

&nbsp;

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>918</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-03-15 14:21:50</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-03-15 19:21:50</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dispatch-paperwork-purgatory</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a-dispatch-from-paperwork-purgatory]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Flashback To A Year Ago</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/flashback-year-ago/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2014 20:51:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=923</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Exactly one year ago today, Nick and I (Cooper) woke up bright and early to drive our crappy 3-door rental car from Reykjavik, Iceland's charming capital, to the tiny fishing village of Vik some 100 miles to the east. Over the next 12 hours, we would swim in an abandoned geothermal pool carved into the side of a mountain, ogle some of the most magnificent waterfalls on this planet, "pilot" the decaying wreck of a U.S. Navy airplane that crashed on the black sand beach in the 1970s, and watch the northern lights dance in the clear night skies. Iceland is easily the most strikingly beautiful place I’ve ever been, and its grandiose, alien landscapes are burned into my memory clear as day.

Not long before we visited Iceland, Nick and I had casually discussed doing the Mongol Rally, and so I think we both saw the weeklong trip as a sort of test run for a much longer excursion to come. It can be exhausting and infuriating to spend so much time in the company of just one other person, and naturally, this trip tested our patience (and our friendship!). But despite a few hiccups here and there, Nick and I had a incredible time in Iceland, and as I reflect on where I was a year ago today (and on that trip at large), I’m filled with nothing but happiness and thanks. I know that this probably sounds sappy and cliche, but it's the truth.

It seems to me that the most unpleasant in-the-moment experiences often produce the most powerful, evocative, and humorous memories down the road. And so while I am quite sure that our trip this summer will have its fair share of unpleasant moments, I know that it will remain with us for the rest of our lives. And that pretty exciting.

Anyway, enough of that. To reward you for your patience, here are a few photos I took on 17 March 2013 (cropped to 16:9 just for fun).

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0260.jpg" alt="DSC_0260" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-949" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0271.jpg" alt="DSC_0271" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-950" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0332.jpg" alt="DSC_0332" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-954" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0292.jpg" alt="DSC_0292" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-951" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0313.jpg" alt="DSC_0313" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-952" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0322.jpg" alt="DSC_0322" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-953" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0334.jpg" alt="DSC_0334" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-955" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0399.jpg" alt="DSC_0399" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-956" />

And a bonus for friendship
<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/DSC_0015.jpg" alt="DSC_0015" width="1000" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-948" />

I really look forward to visually documenting our adventure this summer. To do this correctly, however, I'll need a variety of filters, adapters, hoods, caps, tripods, tripod heads, cards, straps, batteries, and other doodads (not to mention the cameras and lenses themselves). So, if you have any old camera gear lying around that you think might come in handy on our trip – or better yet, if you’d like to sponsor the photography and videography components of our trip – don’t hesitate to holler. Rest assured, your donations will be put to good use.

And as always, we’d love to hear your thoughts on our trip, and/or any advice that you might have for us, so feel free to send us a message or leave a comment below.

Over and out.

//Cooper]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>923</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-03-17 15:51:48</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-03-17 20:51:48</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>flashback-year-ago</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[flashbacks-to-a-year-ago]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>20</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Tom Chokel]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>tjchokel@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.coinsafe.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>162.222.169.176</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-20 23:15:39</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-21 04:15:39</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Cooper!

This sounds fucking incredible. I'm very excited for you guys and can't wait to hear about your adventures. If you haven't read it, I'd recommend picking up a copy of Vagabonding by Rolf Potts - not all of it will be relevant to your quest, but it's got some great practical advice on how to deal with life on the road. 

Also, no spending my donation on cooling the earth - those funds are strictly earmarked for creating a good story.

Stay safe, take good notes, and kick somebody out of the group so I can tag along next year!

Tom

P. S. Your website is awesome. Who designed it?]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1395375339.573173046112060546875;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1396391846.0406420230865478515625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Interactive Route Map</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/interactive-route-map/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 19:22:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=988</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Hello again, Rubikhaners!

For those of you who don’t know, Cooper loves making maps. I love looking at maps (and making map legends with comically large north arrows). This winter, we had the opportunity to combine our two (equally impressive) skill sets to create an interactive Crossing the Rubikhan route map for the final project in our geovisualization class. While the end product isn't exactly what our dear professor had in mind ("no compass rose?!?!"), we hope it’ll be an acceptable resource for all of you loyal supporters as you follow us through some of this planet’s remarkable cities. So without further ado, we present to you our map! Click on the image below to launch the real thing.

//Nick

<a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/map.html" target="_blank"><img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/MapLaunchIcon.png" alt="MapLaunchIcon" width="1000" height="564" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-990" /></a>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>988</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-04-04 14:22:21</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-04-04 19:22:21</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>interactive-route-map</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>67</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Patty]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>pattyscheid@yahoo.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.105.251.63</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-06 22:03:00</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-07 03:03:00</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[This is a great map! And so fun to advance through your route. Thanks for this armchair traveling experience.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1396839780.335813045501708984375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1396969423.449511051177978515625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>OH MY GOD WE BOUGHT A CAR</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/we-bought-a-car/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 20:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jenkinsb12]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1002</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Salut! We're thrilled to announce that we have filled the biggest gap in our preparations to drive across Eurasia: we bought a car! Thanks to our friends over at eBay (including CEO John Donahoe, a Dartmouth College alumnus), the buying process was relatively easy—aside from 15 extremely stressful minutes huddled around a computer together, watching the clock tick down on the auction, hoping someone wouldn't swoop in at the end to snipe the car with a better offer.
<div>

Our (hopefully) trusty steed is a silver 2004 Suzuki Alto, which is a small 5-door hatchback. While we have yet to name our car, we're pretty confident it's a she-mobile. You can check her out in the pictures below. She's currently located in England, but fortunately for us, her steering wheel is on the proper side of the dashboard. (Most of the UK-based teams participating in the rally choose to purchase RHD cars, and are consequently forced to drive on wrong side of the road for the 98% of the trip that isn't on their strange little island. Suckers!)

Our mistress comes equipped with a 1.1L engine, which produces a whopping 62 horsepower—or the equivalent of two Nicks. She also boasts anti-anti-lock brakes, airbags (read: trashbags filled with air), and a host of other modern conveniences, such as headlights. Her 8 inches of clearance should be more than enough to carry us over all those Kazakh potholes and Gobi Desert rivers we're bound to encounter. Granted, she's not exactly a Land Rover, but this particular model has a surprisingly excellent reputation for all-terrain driving. We have high hopes that she'll get us to Ulaanbaatar. Anyway, without further ado, here's a first look at our new baby girl:

<img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-1005" style="line-height: 1.5em;" alt="car pic1" src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/car-pic1-1024x874.jpg" width="960" height="819" />
<div>Before our gal is roadworthy, however, she needs a bit of TLC. Our friend Errol, who lives across the pond and runs a little company called <a href="http://www.coastlinecampers.com/" target="_blank">Coastline Campers</a>, has agreed to take care of some of the most critical maintenance tasks: replacing the filters, brakepads, tires, sparkplugs, and  other things that sound disturbingly unfamiliar to us, fitting a sump guard and a snorkel, and adorning our little Alto with some menacing racing stripes.</div>
<div>

We've got some other modifications in mind—like affixing a massive stuffed yak's head to the roof, and adding some sweet hydraulics. Inspired by the video below, we've even considered souping up the suspension a bit:
<p align="center"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/tM_CnjdiTCo" height="480" width="853" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0"></iframe></p>
 We'd love to hear your suggestions, so feel free to leave a comment below. And of course, if you'd like to help us pay for any of these modifications, head on over to our <a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate" target="_blank">donation page</a>—we'll be eternally grateful for your support.

</div>
In any case, here are a couple more pictures of our gal, just for good measure:

</div>
<div><img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-1006" style="line-height: 1.5em;" alt="car pic2" src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/car-pic2-1024x607.jpg" width="960" height="569" /></div>
<div></div>
<div><img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-1007" alt="car pic3" src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/car-pic3-1024x796.jpg" width="960" height="746" /></div>
We'll definitely keep you posted on her transformation from granny-mobile into tarmac-eater.
<div></div>
<div>Cheers for now,</div>
<div>Benjie</div>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1002</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-04-16 15:14:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-04-16 20:14:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>we-bought-a-car</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[oh-my-god-we-bought-a-car]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>95</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Mike Thomas]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>Club5141@msn.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>97.75.106.98</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-16 15:43:51</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-16 20:43:51</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Hopefully a couple of you numbskulls know how to handle a manual transmission.......]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1397681031.7088260650634765625;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1397755683.18375301361083984375;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>102</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Rick Wilson]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>limonaia@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>207.170.198.199</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-18 15:48:07</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-18 20:48:07</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[You guys need some <a href="http://forums.bowsite.com/tf/pics/00small52448057.JPG" rel="nofollow">bull bars</a> on that thing to carry road kill for <a href="http://www.moscow-russia-insiders-guide.com/images/barbecue-tips-shashlik-3.jpg" rel="nofollow">shashlik</a>!]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1397854088.07958889007568359375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1398014386.3327720165252685546875;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Where did Shav go??</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/where-did-shav-go/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 21:36:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1033</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Life is full of ups and downs. With the Rubikhans’ gain of one (1) car; we have also lost one (1) team member. It is with heavy hearts that we bid Keshav daraa uulzi (“good bye” in Mongolian, but Shav’ll never know that).  Silly Keshav got a silly job in silly India working for the silly MIT Poverty Action Lab. We’re all very proud of him. 

For those of you who don’t know—looking at you, Shav’s parents—Shav will be spending the next 14 months in semi-rural India doing economic development research and living in conditions that rival…well, his current room on campus (pictures mercifully omitted). His boss has already stressed to him the importance of “bulking up” in order to gain the respect of the locals with whom he’ll be interacting and developing business/romantic relationships.

Naturally, we tried everything possible to reconcile his adventure with our own—including rerouting our trip through India to drop him off. Unfortunately Afghani, Pakistani, and Chinese visas aren’t as easy to acquire as you might think. And none of us really want to give our family heart attacks. Silly subcontinent. 

We’ll miss Keshav dearly on our long drive—his thirst for weird places and extreme circumstance would have been invaluable on our journey. But we’re pumped that he’s ditching us for an incredible adventure of his own—it’s really the only valid excuse he could have given. While it means that our inevitable goodbye has been pushed up from September to June, we can’t wait to trade stories from some of the most obscure corners of the globe. 

We’ll miss you, Shav. Crossing the Rubikhan won’t be the same without you. But at least our car will be lighter…

Keep donating away <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/donate/" title="here" target="_blank">here</a> and maybe we'll be able to buy a replacement Shav! Just kidding but we would still like to afford a sump guard so Kazakh rocks don't split our fuel tank in two.

Thanks for reading!

Nick
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1033</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-04-22 16:36:29</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-04-22 21:36:29</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>where-did-shav-go</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Of Backpacks and Beacons</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/of-backpacks-and-beacons/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 21:17:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1041</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[What do you do when you lose the "nugget" part of your phone charger, and can't be bothered to replace it? Cooper found himself in this very predicament earlier this week. His solution? To ziptie our GoalZero Nomad 7 solar panel to his backpack, and recharge his phone using the power of the sun. Even in the absence of direct sunlight – what's that all about, anyway? – the panel has worked flawlessly. Plus, since wearable technologies are totally en vogue right now, Cooper is racking up some serious bonus points with all the fashion-forward ladies of Dartmouth (or so he claims). In any case, the Nomad 7 – and the other solar devices that <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/captains-log-february-doldrums-lead-to-march-madness/" target="_blank">GoalZero sent us</a> – will definitely come in handy while we traverse the power-less Central Asian steppe. Especially since we haven't been able to find a 1,000-mile-long extension cord with an American-style three-prong plug. Yet. 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/P5010193.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1039" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/P5010199.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1040" />

Actually, the untethered power supplied by this solar panel has proven quite useful over the past few days, as Cooper has been testing several different GPS tracking apps in preparation for the rally. While we'll probably invest in a dedicated GPS tracker, the iPhone's built-in GPS offers a cheap alternative – albeit a very power-hungry one. We want to keep you abreast of our whereabouts, and so Cooper is working on integrating this data into our existing <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/interactive-route-map/" target="_blank">interactive route map</a> in realtime. Stay tuned for details on that. And in the meantime, you can check out Cooper's movements over the last week. Can you identify his residence? Hint: it's not actually the computer science building. Or the middle of the Connecticut River.

<iframe width='100%' height='600px' frameBorder='0' src='https://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v4/reldresalwashington.inc6jofj/attribution,zoompan,zoomwheel.html?access_token=pk.eyJ1IjoicmVsZHJlc2Fsd2FzaGluZ3RvbiIsImEiOiI4dW1WR0VNIn0.Qjo9m18c2DGavmMXa3pVPw'></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1041</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-05-02 16:17:13</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-05-02 21:17:13</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>of-backpacks-and-beacons</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Food is Weird</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/food-is-weird/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 18:55:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1065</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[As we are now only two months from launch, Benjie is getting more and more conscious that there will be no escargot (outside of France) and my research tells me that there is no Chipotle in the Asian Steppe (yet). So instead, we’ve looked into some of the fine cuisine we’ll encounter when the Safeways start to become Less-than-Safeways.

<strong>10 Weird Foods We’re Trying Before Ulaanbaatar
</strong>
<strong>1. Kokorec (Turkey):</strong> whenever I eat sheep intestines, I think about how much better they would taste barbecued. No longer! This popular street food is served quite spicy, regrettably masking the sweet sweet smell of intestine. Rumor has it that EBAs will soon offer a Buffalo Kokorec Pizza. 

<strong>2. Goat Blood Soup (Kyrgyzstan):</strong> unlike misnomers like “Prairie Oysters” and “Friendly’s,” this Kyrgyz delicacy is exactly what it sounds like. 

<strong>3. Beshbarmak (also Kyrgyzstan):</strong> called “Five Fingers” because it is eaten with one’s hands, this dish is a variety of diced meat and noodles, the centerpiece of which is a boiled sheep’s head (I guess the intestines are exported to Turkey). As we mentioned in an earlier post, the head is given to the most honored guest with other parts of the animal distributed to different family members according to ritual.

<strong>4. Somsa (Uzbekistan):</strong> this cute looking pouch of dough is filled with whatever you’d like, which is more often than not the entirety of a large mammal of your (non-English speaking cook’s) choosing.

<strong>5. Zungenwurst (Germany):</strong> a sausage made from pork blood and pickled ox tongue. And here you are thinking we wouldn’t face anything foul (or fowl) until Turkey (fowl)!

<strong>6. Airag (Mongolia):</strong> not really a food but fermented horse milk doesn’t exactly fall into the ‘drink’ category either. Important note: if you are registering a Tier I Yurt party, you are allowed to serve fermented milk from no more than two (2) horse’s udders. There will be one walk-through.

<strong>7. Plov (Everywhere):</strong> this amorphous dish isn’t gross in and of itself but past rally-ers tell us that it will become a staple of our diet once we cross east of the Caspian. It’s predominantly a rice dish, but chefs throw in whatever little pieces of meat and vegetables are within arm’s reach—so any of these first six dishes are fair game.

<strong>8. Boodog (Mongolia):</strong> presumably named because of its capacity to scare, this is a goat carcass hung upside down, de-boned (?) and flipped inside out. It’s then cooked with a blowtorch. Because kitchens are overrated.

<strong>9. Lososova Sandwich at Bageterie Boulevard (Czech Republic):</strong> probably the best item on the menu in Prague’s best casual sandwich shop, the Lososova combines fresh smoked salmon from the Czech Republic’s finest coastal fishing villages with unmatched Czech hospitality (they only sometimes grunt when you pay with a 200 kC bill).

<strong>10. Hakarl (Iceland):</strong> you caught us, we’re not traveling through Iceland. But Cooper and I just wanted to show off that during our adventure in Iceland last year, we tried the infamous Hakarl...which is putrified shark meat. This “dish” is prepared by burying a whole shark under the sand for months until it grows a thick layer of mold. (Incidentally, the shark meat is fatally toxic when untreated.) The shark is then unearthed, the mold scraped off, and the shark diced into tiny, bite sized pieces. These pieces are served raw. See photo evidence below:

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Hakarl.jpg" alt="Hakarl" width="1280" height="720" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1075" />

More updates soon! For now we're looking to afford <del datetime="2014-05-09T19:42:58+00:00">spare</del> missing parts for our beloved new car in case it gets sick so feel free to donate <a href="www.crossingtherubikhan.com/donate" title="here" target="_blank">here</a>!

Until next time,
Nick
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1065</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-05-09 13:55:52</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-05-09 18:55:52</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>food-is-weird</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>These Are A Few Of Our Favorite Things</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/our-wishlist/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 21:28:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1077</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Merhaba! (That's hello in Turkish).<b style="color: #000000;"> </b>Our July launch date is rapidly approaching, but truth be told, we still lack a considerable amount of mission-critical equipment. This includes things like a tent, a tool set, and lots and lots of baby wipes. So, if you own and are willing to part with any of the items on the following list – or are willing to "sponsor" us through the purchase of one or more of these things – please don't hesitate to reach out to us. They don't need to be the latest and greatest models – they just have to help us reach Mongolia! We plan to donate most, if not all, of this equipment to charity once we arrive in Ulaanbaatar. And we'll happily <a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate" target="_blank">reward</a> you for your contributions.

Fortunately, we've already managed to secure some of the most expensive equipment we'll need through sponsorships from two companies that we are very excited to be working with. <a href="http://www.goalzero.com" target="_blank">GoalZero</a>, an innovator of high-quality portable solar power products, has generously sent us two solar panel charging units as well as a super-bright lantern for our campsite, and speakers that blast music for 20 hours on a mere 2 hour charge so we can take a break from listening to Nick's jokes. In addition, <a href="http://www.roadpost.com" target="_blank">Roadpost Satcom</a> will soon be providing us with a satellite phone and internet router that will create a WiFi hotspot for us literally in the middle of the Gobi Desert - pretty cool, eh? That means we'll be able to keep you all updated no matter where we are. But don't worry, transmitting data is far too expensive to do all of the time, so chances are still high that we'll spend plenty of time completely lost.

Fortunately, the rest of the equipment we need is much less expensive--but as we've already discovered, these small expenses can add up quickly. To make things easier for you, we've even prepared an <a href="http://amzn.com/w/1BNZH15BXHE0D" target="_blank">Amazon wishlist</a>, which'll allow you to order the things we need and ship them to Benjie's house where we are staging things before our departure to the UK. You can sort sort the items by priority and price (most of them are less than $40). We'll do our best to keep this list updated.

On a related note, if you work for a company that produces or sells any of these products, and you'd like to arrange a sponsorship agreement with our team, don't hesitate to <a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#contact" target="_blank">contact us</a>. You can can learn more about the perks of sponsorship on our <a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#sponsor" target="_blank">sponsors page</a>. Alternatively, you can make a direct donation right <a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate" target="_blank">here</a>. Anyway, here's some of the stuff we still need:

[one_half]
<ul>
	<li>Lightweight cookset</li>
	<li>Lightweight canister camp stove</li>
	<li><del>Three-person pop-up tent</del></li>
	<li><del>Tent groundcloth/footprint</del></li>
	<li>Compact folding chairs (x3)</li>
	<li>Compact sleeping pads (x3)</li>
	<li>Compact camp table</li>
	<li>Rope hammock</li>
	<li>Strong rope (several meters)</li>
	<li><del>Short hatchet/axe</del></li>
	<li>Folding table</li>
	<li><del>Portable first aid kit</del></li>
</ul>
[/one_half]
<ul>
&nbsp;
	<li>Basic automotive tool kit</li>
	<li>MREs (6-pack/half-case)</li>
	<li>Car traction mats/ladders</li>
	<li><del>Jumper cables</del></li>
	<li><del>Tire pressure gauge</del></li>
	<li>Scissor jack</li>
	<li>Tire iron set</li>
	<li><del>SPOT Gen3 Satellite GPS Tracker</del></li>
	<li>GoPro telescoping monopod</li>
	<li>GoPro chest harness</li>
	<li>GoPro suction cup mount</li>
</ul>
&nbsp;

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1077</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-05-10 16:28:16</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-05-10 21:28:16</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>our-wishlist</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>private</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_post_restored_from</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:3:{s:20:"restored_revision_id";i:1152;s:16:"restored_by_user";i:4;s:13:"restored_time";i:1401229308;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[wishlist]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>500</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Carol ladd]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>cladd@comcast.net</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>24.22.92.19</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-06-14 11:50:46</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-06-14 16:50:46</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Cooper, Ive got 2 rolls of Duct Tape, one silver the other black.  Let me know if you still need them and if you are planning on being in Portland. I could drop them off at your parent's house.  Carol]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1402764646.558001041412353515625;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1402957915.460688114166259765625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Going in Circles</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/going-in-circles/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 21:17:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1084</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We owe a big thank you to our friend Nick – no, not <em>teammate</em> Nick – for providing us with some ace driving lessons yesterday. We mashed the living daylights out of the clutch in Nick's Audi, but he barely batted an eyelash. This was actually (teammate) Nick's first time driving a manual transmission, and by all accounts, he did a pretty good job! Benjie managed to capture Nick's first few seconds behind the wheel:

http://instagram.com/p/n_12V2glDb/

Unfortunately, we're not sure if <a href="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/we-bought-a-car/" target="_blank">our 2004 Suzuki Alto</a> also comes equipped with a weighted shifter, a direct-shift gearbox, a dual clutch transmission, or any of the Audi's other drivetrain-related bells and whistles. And we're definitely not sure what any of these things actually do. But we do know that our car has four wheels, an engine, and a steering wheel, so we think we're in pretty good shape.

*UPDATE: our mechanic friend in the UK reports that our Alto needs new brake pads, but also has a working horn. So we're definitely in good shape. Stay tuned for more!

*UDPATE #2: on Monday, the Rubikhans got their first lesson in auto repair: Moral of the story? We must not destroy our Alto's transmission!

http://instagram.com/p/oAIQp6AlLh/

//The Rubikhans]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1084</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-05-10 16:17:43</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-05-10 21:17:43</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>going-in-circles</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[learning-to-drive]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Friendships and Sponsorships</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/friendships-and-sponsorships/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2014 21:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1164</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Dear Friends, Family, and Other Loyal Followers,

I write to you as our time at Dartmouth comes to a close—tomorrow our family members roll in and we prepare to say our long goodbyes. (To Dartmouth—not to our parents, hopefully.) Cooper, Benjie, and I have spent this past week maximizing time with the closest friends we’ve ever had and reflecting on the past four years—on our adventures, misadventures, our stresses and our joys. 

Never has it been so apparent that the important moments, the times that will stick with us as we go on to Lyon, Bishkek, and New York (spelling?) are the times when we abandoned the comforts of everyday living and did something crazy. When Cooper and I traversed a raging Icelandic river in order to reach an abandoned swimming pool, when team member-emeritus Keshav and I found the best looking gas masks in all of Central Europe, and when Benjie descended into the Parisian catacombs, but not the ones you’re thinking of.

Reflecting on the tremendous memories we made in our four years here has reaffirmed why we’re doing this—why we’re dropping everything to take a piece-of-junk Suzuki 10,000 miles across some of the most remote landscapes on Earth. We’re doing it because leaving Dartmouth will not mean the end of adventures together. The experiences we’ll share on the Rally will be some of the most incredible we’ve ever had. And they’ll last a lifetime.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/team_photo-011.jpg" alt="team_photo-01" width="940" height="580" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-511" />

As we mope and hug and stay up way too late, we’ve found solace from nostalgia by thinking forward to the Rally. We’ve been extremely fortunate to land a couple of key sponsorships in the past couple of weeks. We’d like to give a big shout out to Jason at <a href="http://www.visionsign.net/" title="Vision Sign" target="_blank">Vision Sign</a> for generously taking care of our car decals (reader vote: racing stripes, flames, or a life-size sticker of Ruth Bader Ginsburg?). Thanks to Vision Sign's help, we might actually be able to conceal the overall crappiness of our car! You can check out some of their sweet work by clicking on the image below, or heading to their <a href="https://www.facebook.com/visionsignDMV?fref=ts" title="Vision Sign Facebook" target="_blank">Facebook page</a>.

<a href="http://www.visionsign.net/"><img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/Vision_Sign_logo-01.png" alt="Vision_Sign_logo-01" width="800" height="300" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1169" /></a>

We’re still in the market for a bunch of smaller items that could make all the difference in the world to us. Check out our wish list <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/registry/wishlist/1BNZH15BXHE0D/ref=cm_sw_su_w" title="here" target="_blank">here</a> and see if there’s anything you’d like to sponsor for us.  We’ll even name it after you! The Jen R. S. Doenor Memorial Tire Iron Set has a certain ring to it, doesn’t it?

Talk to you when we’re college graduates!

Nick
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1164</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-06-05 16:38:45</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-06-05 21:38:45</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>friendships-and-sponsorships</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[sponsorships-and-friendships]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Excuse Us While We Graduate</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/excuse-us-while-we-graduate/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2014 00:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1180</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The title of this post says it all, really. On Sunday, Benjie, Cooper, and Nick received their undergraduate diplomas, capping off four years of hard work (and hard play) at Dartmouth. Here are a couple very sweaty photos taken right after the ceremony. 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/P6080433.jpg" alt="Graduation1" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1181" />

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/P6080442.jpg" alt="Graduation2" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1182" />

To our dear families: thank you for your tireless support over the past four years. And thank you for sanctioning our plan to drive to Mongolia, crazy and ambitious though it may be. We probably would have done it without your approval, so we're glad that you're behind it as well. 

Full steam ahead!

]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1180</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-06-10 19:58:34</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-06-11 00:58:34</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>excuse-us-while-we-graduate</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>I Scream for Ice Cream</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/i-scream-for-ice-cream/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 04:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1246</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We love ice cream—so much, in fact, that for a while, we considered driving to Mongolia in a fully functioning ice cream truck (much like <a href="http://image.minitruckinweb.com/f/events/west/1109mt_danger_zone_2011_custom_truck_show/33390154/1109mt-03%2Bdanger-zone-2011-custom-truck-show%2Bice-cream-truck.jpg" target="_blank">this one</a>). Sadly, however, we reluctantly abandoned that dream when we realized that camping gear takes precedence over delicious frozen snacks. Undeterred, however, we have settled for the next best thing: a partnership with <a href="http://coolmoonicecream.com/" title="Cool Moon" target="_blank">Cool Moon Ice Cream Co.</a>, a fantastic ice cream shop located in the heart of downtown Portland. 

<a href="http://coolmoonicecream.com/" target="_blank"><img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/CoolMoon_Logo-01.png" alt="CoolMoon_Logo-01" width="800" height="400" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1250" /></a>

Unlike most ice cream shops, Cool Moon makes all of its flavors on-site, one batch at a time, just meters away from the dipping cabinets. Consequently, the wizards in the kitchen are constantly experimenting with different ingredients and prototyping new flavors. They've engineered with some truly tastetacular delicacies, such as Thai Iced Tea, Kulfi (a take on the pistachio-, cardamom-, and rosewater-based Indian dessert), and Oakshire Espresso Stout (made with real beer, of course). However, the Cool Moon kitchen staff put the same amount of effort and care into their traditional flavors—based on our own experience, we can confidently say that Cool Moon's Indonesian Vanilla can't be beat, and that the shop's myriad berry flavors, most of which are produced using Oregon-grown (and, in the case of marionberry, Oregon-engineered!) berries, are downright addicting. Incidentally, Cooper spent two summers working at Cool Moon, and he makes an effort to visit the shop—and to stock his freezer—whenever he's in town. It's really that good.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/DSC_0025.jpg" alt="DSC_0025" width="1200" height="798" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1259" />
(Above: patrons of all ages and sizes can enjoy Cool Moon's chill ambience)

And now, to the <em>really</em> good stuff: to support our journey and our charitable causes, <strong>Cool Moon is producing a limited-edition ice cream flavor in honor of Team Crossing the Rubikhan!!</strong> A portion of the ice cream's sales will go into the team's fund. The flavor is called NON SENSU COMMUNI, or NO COMMON SENSE. The title needs no explanation, but it’s the ingredients that make this flavor truly spectacular: a rich swirl of <del>goat blood</del> Oregon raspberries and three kinds of nuts (again, no explanation needed) blended into Cool Moon’s signature sweet cream base. It’s sure to be a crowd pleaser.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/DSC_0012-680x1024.jpg" alt="DSC_0012" width="680" height="1024" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1257" />
(Above: ice cream master-chef Amy, hard at work. Note the tattoo!)

Now, you’re probably asking yourselves, “how can I get my hands on some of this deliciousness?” Unfortunately, the ice cream is only available to local supporters, as we don’t have a dry ice budget. However, Portland residents are in luck: <strong>Cooper will be doling out free samples of the ice cream at Cool Moon on First Thursday (July 3rd), from 6:00pm to 8:00pm</strong>. Cool Moon is located on the corner of 11th Avenue and Johnson Street, just across the street to Jamison Square. Stop by, enjoy the ice cream, and say a prayer for Cooper and the team! 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/DSC_0002.jpg" alt="DSC_0002" width="1200" height="798" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1256" />
(Above: Cool Moon owner Eva Bernhard serves up a scoop of deliciousness)

Again, here are the details of the event:

<h5>What:</h5> <strong>A free sampling of NON SENSU COMMUNI, Cool Moon's Mongol Rally-inspired ice cream flavor</strong>
<h5>When:</h5> <strong> Thursday, July 3rd, from 6:00pm to 8:00pm
<h5>Where:</h5> <strong> Cool Moon Ice Cream, 1105 NW Johnson St. (at the intersection of 11th Ave. and Johnson St., across the street from Jamison Square)
<h5>Why:</h5> <strong> To show your support for Team Crossing the Rubikhan, to chat with Cooper about the upcoming trip, and to induge in a delicious frozen treat!</strong>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1246</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-06-28 23:46:15</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-06-29 04:46:15</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>i-scream-for-ice-cream</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>765</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[LAR]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>larmcqueen@msn.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://larmcqueen@msn.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.115.151.112</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-05 21:14:41</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-06 02:14:41</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I have faith in you, Cooper.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1404612881.957366943359375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1404762735.4866430759429931640625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Here Today, There Tomorrow...</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/here-today-there-tomorrow/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 15:15:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1315</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Greetings everyone,

Well, the day has finally arrived—after over a year of plotting, planning, and preparing, we have packed our bags, charged our camera batteries, and said our goodbyes, and in just a couple of hours, we'll fly to London to begin our grand adventure. 

For months, we’ve looked forward to this trip with tremendous anticipation. And yet, until just a few days ago, we weren't even sure if we could pull it off. But now that our affairs are (mostly) in order, the reality of the situation is finally sinking in. It’s both exhilarating and anxiety-inducing. It seems nearly impossible to account for the myriad little details that might rear their ugly heads at some point: do we need more than one spare tire? How much money will we need for bribes? Do the Turkmen border guards allow prescription drugs into the country? Did Nick just leave his passport on the copy machine at the FedEx store? (Yeah, but no worries, we got it back).

That being said, at this point, we accept the fact that we can’t think of everything, and that some things are simply out of our control. Things will go wrong, and they should—that’s part of the experience, and one of our main goals for the trip is to live in the moment and expect the unexpected. So when we get held up at the Russia-Mongolia border for two days in the middle of a snowstorm and only get through by giving up a hundred bucks and our last bottle of Jack Daniel's, we’ll be smiling, because those are the parts of the trip that might turn out to be the most memorable.

Speaking of bribes, we could still use some extra cash because truly it’s impossible to anticipate how much we will need. Many of you have already donated, and we are incredibly appreciative. But if anyone else is inclined to throw a few bucks our way, we can assure you that they won’t go to waste. Unless you think that giving them to a corrupt Kazakh police officer is a waste, in which case we won’t be offended if you choose to keep them for yourself. You can easily donate by <a href="http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/blog" title="Blog" target="_blank">clicking right here</a>. In return for your support, we can offer you some sweet rewards, like postcards, trinkets, and even personal video messages from the road. And don’t forget, a portion of your donation will go to our two charities: SOS Children’s Villages, and Cool Earth.

Regardless of whether you’ve donated, we hope you’ll enjoy following along with us. We tested our satellite internet router yesterday and it works perfectly, so we will be updating this page throughout the trip with pictures and anecdotes from the road. And lastly, if you’ve already donated more than $25, please <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/13XRsQQbZKVYTJHnIpe6w6W8fgRDtVoMXqNGp1cqSibk/viewform?usp=send_form" title="Donor Address" target="_blank">click here and enter your address</a> so that we can send your rewards to you!
 
A huge thank you again for all of your support, and we'll update you from London. Alea Yakta Est!

Cheers,
Benjie, Cooper, and Nick

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P5010229-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1316" />
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1315</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-07-13 10:15:24</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-07-13 15:15:24</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>here-today-there-tomorrow</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Touchdown in England</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/touchdown-in-england/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 21:34:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1333</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Hello everyone!

We’ve been in this strange land called England for nearly two days now—reconciling the peculiarities of the land (left side of the road, silly accents, no trash cans) with how much more peculiar the lands we’re about to experience are going to be.

After toasting America in an airport bar—by watching the World Cup final (naturally)—we were one overnight flight, rush-hour tube ride, and double-decker bus away from our temporary base in London. A friend from school has generously taken us in, providing us with the finest lodgings we’re likely to see for quite a while. We’d like to thank Sophia and the whole Johnston family for making our adjustment as comfortable as possible by giving us a cozy home base, beds, and delicious first dinner...and for joining me (Nick) on an impromptu trip to the pharmacy, because it’s better to get food poisoning here than in Kazakhstan!

To stave off sleep on the first day, we poked around Chelsea, stumbled upon the noontime changing of the guards at Buckingham Palace, met a friend of Benjie’s for a couple pints, and hopped back on the Piccadilly line for a quick pre-dinner siesta. Cooper and a food-poisoned Nick (he’s better now, Mom) returned to the Johnston household while Benjie chose to sit under a tree in Hyde Park and write in his journal, because of course he did.

With a feast in our bellies, we promptly passed out so that we could awake in time for our super-early (11:45am) train to our car in Canterbury. Spoiler alert: we still missed our train.

But we made the next one, and soon arrived at the workshop of our mechanic friend Errol to find our noble beast replete with roof rack, sump guard, and two giant monster truck headlights. She looks like an awkward bug. But she's our awkward bug.

Benjie took the wheel first, and thankfully succeeded in not embarrassing us as we navigated the manual car off the farm and directly onto the highway. When Cooper and Nick tried their hand at the wheel later, a quick series of stall-outs, including a few in the middle of an intersection, dissuaded them from taking it the rest of the way to the hotel. So with Benjie at the wheel, we drove into the coastal town of Gillingham for a few brews and some fish & chips.

Back to London tomorrow. Below are a few photos from the past couple days. We wanted to wait until decorating the car to post pictures. Stay tuned for her official unveiling!

Nick, Cooper, and Benjie

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7130457-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1334" />One last round in the States

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7130463-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1335" />Benjie and Cooper, worried about Nick's health, ordered him a special Asian vegetarian meal for the flight.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7140484-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1337" />London, from above

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7140506-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1338" />For whatever reason, Aston Martin has decided to enter the Mongol Rally market.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7140512-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1340" />According to the kind Chinese tourists we met, the Queen of England lives here

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7140509-768x1024.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="768" height="1024" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1339" />Proof that we made it to London!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7140515-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1341" />Entry #2 in the beer diary

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7150003-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1343" />Our ride to Canterbury.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7150008-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1344" />Nick looks pensively out the window. More in this riveting series to follow.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7150015-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1346" />Our mechanic friend Errol hands Benjie the keys

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7150022-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1347" />The car's German owner's manual will certainly come in handy (for kindling)]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1333</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-07-15 16:34:05</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-07-15 21:34:05</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>touchdown-in-england</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1333]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2187</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Nancy]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>nachurch57@msn.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>75.164.229.141</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-05 21:08:55</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-06 02:08:55</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[But it says to ALWAYS LEAVE IT IN THE CAR; IT CONTAINS IMPORTANT INFORMATION ABOUT SAFETY, SERVICE AND WARRANTIES!I hope you're doing OK without it.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407290936.04938411712646484375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407948053.942616939544677734375;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Last Day(s) in London</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/last-days-in-london/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 23:37:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1377</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Hello everyone! 

We've spent the past few days running a few last-minute errands in London, purchasing some crucial rally equipment like car tools and garish Hawaiian shirts, and, in our spare time, checking off some London tourism highlights. 

Today was an eventful day for us, as we went to pick up our car where we had left it in a car park in the London suburbs for the past few days, only to discover that the battery was completely dead. Fortunately, we found some nice chaps at a nearby auto repair shop who jumped it for us, and we're hoping that if we run the car a bit every day from now on she'll be okay. We do understand that there is a fine line between optimism and naïveté but knock on aluminum we won't have to cross it. 

After completing a jigsaw puzzle packing job we made it to Battersea Park where we were greeted by the most absurd collection of people and cars you will ever see. We chatted with tons of interesting characters who are all a bit nuts and very excited to get on the road. Tomorrow we will head out of London and make a beeline for the English Channel to hop on a ferry to France, and hopefully we'll be somewhere near Cologne, Germany tomorrow night. Stay tuned for more updates from the road! And don't forget that you you can also follow us on <a href="http://www.facebook.com/crossingtherubikhan" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and Instagram @<a href="http://www.instagram.com/therubikhans" target="_blank">therubikhans</a>. Below are some pictures from the past few days. 

Deuces, 
Benjie, Nick and Cooper 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7160028-768x1024.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="768" height="1024" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1357" />Benjie devours his first full English breakfast, minus the black pudding – there are plenty more opportunities for gross culinary specialties ahead of us!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7170052-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1360" />Enjoying our personal tour of the Royal Geographical Society

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7170058-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1361" />Almost there?

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7160040-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1359" />Benjie ponders life, while riding the bus

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7160050-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1376" />The bus drivers drive like maniacs here!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7180070-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1362" />Old and new: St. Paul's Cathedral and the Millennium Bridge

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7180089-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1363" />Reppin' our Cool Moon apparel in front of the London Eye!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7180101-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1365" />Boris Bikes: the best way to get around town

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7180107-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1366" />Another beer-sodden team photo 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190120-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1367" />Loading up the car. Don't worry – more photos are coming!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190123-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1368" />Our modest steed, fully packed and loaded

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190131-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1370" />Benjie loves America! (And sunsets)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190126-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1369" />A glimpse of some of the cars at the Battersea Park pre-launch gathering

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190134-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1372" />Pre-launch warehouse party

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190133-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1371" />In memoriam of our dear teammate emeritus

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190140-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1373" />Benjie flaunts his one-way ticket to adventureland, provided by these loony Austrians

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190145-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1374" />...and another one of the team

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7190146-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1375" />One last glimpse of Chelsea Bridge. See you next time!


]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1377</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-07-19 18:37:39</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-07-19 23:37:39</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>last-days-in-london</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>1556</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[The old Bonegypsy]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>jeffreyljthomas@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>73.37.111.65</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-20 10:46:11</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-20 15:46:11</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Good on ya', mates! Good luck and safe journey.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1405871177.431395053863525390625;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406017502.7722990512847900390625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Life in the Slow Lane</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/life-in-the-slow-lane/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 18:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1386</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Hello from Prague!

It’s been a whirlwind of driving so far and we’ve safely made it out of Western Europe into the warm embrace of Central Europe’s economic, cultural, and only center.

We awoke at the crack of dawn yesterday to join the ~250 other teams at the Mongol Rally starting line in London’s Battersea Park. After waiting a couple hours for our turn to process out of the park and begin our journey (read: get the h*ll on the road already) we finagled our car off the steep platform that served as the official launch and promptly slammed our sump guard into the ground. Five feet into the Rally and our car already has battle scars.

Needless to say, we powered on — and made great time to the English Channel ferry, where we reunited with dozens of other Rally teams. After a ferry ride chatting with the other teams, napping, and cautiously watching our car to make sure it didn’t fall into the channel, we made it to France.

Thirty minutes later we made it out of France and to Veurne, a picturesque Belgian town where my (Nick’s) great-grandmother saved and resurrected a bombed-out hotel just after WWI. And we found the plaque to prove it! 

After receiving marriage advice from a local (and inebriated) couple, we hit the road again and drove straight through to Germany. We were disappointed to race through Belgium, passing up the chance to visit Bruges and Ghent, which were just off the highway. But for the first couple days our goal has been singular: get to Prague.

Making the mistake of not booking a room beforehand, we tried our luck hostel-searching in central Cologne. We ran into two other Ralliers at a gas station on the way in, and we caravanned on into town looking like a fun-sized version of an expedition party. Cologne was gorgeous, even at 11 at night, and apparently a bunch of other people thought so too because neither of the youth hostels we stopped into had space for us — although our new friends lucked out with a couple beds (they only had two left). 

So we learned our lesson to book our hostels ahead of time and we tried our luck back out on the highway where we promptly found a traveler’s motel. We pulled up to the motel where a little sign directed us to go to reception, which was a quarter mile back down the road in a service station. Skeptical, we walked to the station where sure enough we found the reception and sure enough they had a room for us. It seemed like we were the only guests in the creepy, dimly lit building but we didn’t care. We had beds, we had beers, and we could promptly pass out. 

Today has mercifully been less eventful. Crossing central Germany has taught us that while German cars are extremely fast, German trucks are still incredibly slow. And on a two-lane highway, there’s no middle ground (or middle lane) so we stuck to the right, sporadically finding the cajones to pass a lumbering lorry.

Several hundred kilometers and one near-fuel emergency later, we safely arrived in Prague.

Now excuse us while Cooper and I have a couple Pilsners and drag Benjie around our old stomping grounds. Na zdravi! 

Nick, Cooper, and Benjie

PS these photos really don't do our car justice – we're still waiting for the perfect sunset. Also, our satellite tracker is finally up and running. Stay tuned for the interactive map showing our path and current location.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P71901261-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1397" />Friendly folk at the launch in Battersea

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7200160-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1398" />Benjie shows off our rudimentary auxiliary sound system, courtesy of <a href="http://goalzero.com" target="_blank">Goal Zero</a>

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7200156-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1387" />7:00am team photo at Battersea...Cooper is still waking up

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7200166-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1388" />Fiending for <a href="http://www.coolmoonicecream.com" target="_blank">Cool Moon</a> ice cream on the ferry!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7200170-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1389" />The central <del>parking lot</del> square of Veurne, Belgium

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7200174-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1390" />Nick discovers the plaque commemorating his great-grandparents

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7200182-1024x768.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="960" height="720" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1392" />Blazing through Germany

]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1386</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-07-21 13:01:07</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-07-21 18:01:07</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>life-in-the-slow-lane</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>1663</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Willie Thomas]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>watdoing57@gmail.cpm</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>24.228.214.250</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-22 10:44:39</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-22 15:44:39</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Forward! Into the past!]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406043879.787868022918701171875;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406322535.3127191066741943359375;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Another Five-Country Day (Plus Croatia and Bosnia)</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/another-five-country-day/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2014 07:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1409</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Our apologies for the lack of recent updates — apparently, wireless internet is scarcer than expected in Central/Eastern Europe. Sorry, mom(s)!
 
Anyway, we write to you from Slavonski Brod, Croatia, after four incredible yet entirely different days. Let's begin with Monday: we arrived in Prague in the early evening, after enduring several hours of thunderstorms and stop-and-go Autobahn traffic. While we only had time for one night in the city, for Nick and Cooper (who studied here in 2012), these 16 hours were a whirlwind of nostalgia and rememberance. It was tough to say our goodbyes come Tuesday morning, but our tears were dried by prospect of the Mongol Rally “Czech Out Party” located at a castle in southern Bohemia. While the location proved to be more field then castle, we had a blast with the other Ralliers, eating, drinking, being merry, and sharing stories from the road. Additionally, our exhaust had been rattling against the chassis since the Battersea launch, so a helpful Aussie helped us patch up our as-yet unnamed steed. 

While we enjoyed sleeping in our too-tall tent for the first time, we had planned to reach Zadar, Croatia, by Wednesday evening  (to meet our good friend Isaac for dinner), and so we had to wake up at the crack of dawn Wednesday morning to hit the road. Fortunately, we were treated to eleven hours of some of the most diverse and spectacular landscapes we'll ever encounter. Beginning in the hilltop towns and golden fields of the southern Czech Republic, we gradually progressed headed into the distinctively Bavarian borderlands of Germany, replete with old timber halls and (we imagine) lederhosen-clad beer maids. Shortly after, we traversed the eastern reaches of the Austrian Alps, before descending into Mediterranean Slovenia, and then cruising across Croatia just in time to catch a spectacular sunset over the Adriatic. And we made our dinner with Isaac (as well as his ever-present sister). 

A thoroughly enjoyable night out in Zadar somehow reenergized us, and we awoke at a reasonable hour Thursday morning, excited to make the famous drive down the Dalmatian Coast to Dubrovnik. The drive took longer than expected, but was just as spectacular as the previous day's: for nearly six hours we hugged the beaches and cliffs overlooking the crystal-clear Adriatic, while faster cars waited (not-so) patiently behind. Benjie videoed himself woo-ing out the window while Nick learned manual in a sort of trial-by-fire manner and Cooper took pictures of Benjie videoing himself and of Nick repeatedly stalling out next to a crowded beach.

We arrived in Dubrovnik in time for a seafood extravaganza dinner in the old city. While Game of Thrones fans may recognize Dubrovnik as the primary inspiration for King's Landing, we recognized it as too crowded, and much preferred the quiet Adriatic beach by our campsite, where we bathed in the azure waters before falling asleep to the not-so-gentle sounds of Benjie's sonorous snoring. 

While the drive down to Dubrovnik was stunning, we realized somewhere along the way that we had kind of cornered ourselves, as the only ways out were either back the way we came or across the slow and potentially dangerous roads of Bosnia or Montenegro. After much deliberation, we decided on an indirect Bosnian route that took us through the picturesque town of Mostar before leading us up the center of the country, past the war-torn capital of Sarajevo, and finally spitting us out on Croatia’s northern fork. 

This turned out to be the best decision we could have made, as Bosnia (and, lest we forget, Herzegovina) was unexpectedly gorgeous. Dramatic mountain landscapes, turquoise rivers, and cool winds accompanied us along the winding roads leading to Sarajevo – not to mention a picturesque <del datetime="2014-07-25T21:33:47+00:00">Bruce Lee statue</del> bridge and a delicious meat-and-bread lunch in Mostar. Aside from an unfortunate Sarajevo traffic jam (smoggy grey rain included), which ultimately precluded a visit into the center of the city, we steadily crawled our way up the country and made it safely back across the Croatian border. We may only be an hour past where we were two days ago, as the crow flies, but this was certainly a worthy detour. And if we were looking for the most direct way, we would’ve flown to Mongolia. 

We arrived in Slavonski Brod utterly famished — although Nick, having already eaten one meat-and-bread meal today, rejected his teammates' pleas for a quick and easy kebab dinner, instead opting for a vegetable-less fish meal at the riverside. Now, we’re looking forward to a good night’s rest before we set off for Serbia and Bulgaria tomorrow morn.

Lastly, we have some exciting news: our satellite tracking device is finally up and running, so you can now monitor our progress in real-time! Click <a href="https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=a9f453c8530592eec" title="Satellite tracking map" target="_blank">here</a> to view the tracking map on a new page.

Thanks for reading!

 -The Rubikhans

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7210184.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="675" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1415" />Ahoj, Praha!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7210186.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1416" />The beer journal: Czech Republic

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7210192.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="900" height="1200" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1417" />Rainy Prague at night

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7220222.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1419" />Zipping through Bohemia

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7220227.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1420" />Flight Chief Jenkins prepares the drone at the Czech Out party. (Note our palatial tent in the background.)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7220229.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1421" />Using our <a href="http://www.goalzero.com" title="Goal Zero" target="_blank">Goal Zero</a> solar panels to charge our phones.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7220245.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1422" />Tossing a frisbee in a Czech field

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7220257.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1423" />Fire dancers at the Czech Out party

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7230343.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1425" />Our "repaired" exhaust

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7230302.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1435" />One of Austria's countless mountain peaks...

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7230330.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1424" />Followed by one of Austria's countless mountain tunnels

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7230376.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1426" />Safe and sound in Zadar, Croatia

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7230395.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1427" />Look who we found! (Hint: it's Isaac)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7240438.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="900" height="1200" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1428" />A roadside vendor's wares, somewhere along the Dalmatian Coast

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7250483.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1433" />Dubrovnik, Croatia, from above

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7240451.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1430" />Celebratory team beers in Dubrovnik

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7240472.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1432" />Tourists. Lots and lots of them

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7250522.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1438" />Caught in a massive traffic jam in northern Bosnia]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1409</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-07-26 02:12:21</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-07-26 07:12:21</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>another-five-country-day</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[five-country-day-and-borders-galore]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>1857</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Walter baetjer]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>wbbaetj@cox.net</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>24.222.254.97</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-26 07:45:38</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-26 12:45:38</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Loving following along on your great adventure. Adding places to my bucket list!  Great photos &amp; write ups keep it coming. Big cocktail party at the blockhouse rast night. Good weather in chester. Annie and Hen leave tomorrow hoj and tommy come Wednesday.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406378738.64574909210205078125;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406413804.5094859600067138671875;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>1870</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Chris Ficwn]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>cbone12@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>96.249.205.146</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-26 16:41:15</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-26 21:41:15</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Y'all are an inspiration .. hope you're having the time of your lives. Pics are epic and lovin' these updates. keep 'em coming. Live it up! Cheers, Chris G]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406410875.536695003509521484375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406413797.8084170818328857421875;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>1915</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[The old Bonegypsy]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>jeffreyljthomas@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>73.37.111.65</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-28 11:41:47</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-28 16:41:47</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Can't get enough of your adventure blog...hope you can stop to smell the kebabs along the way...]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406565707.1948230266571044921875;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Serbulgaristan(bul)</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/serbulgarstanbul/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 15:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1444</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Greetings from Istanbul!

We’re giving ourselves – and our car – some much needed rest in this sprawling, vibrant metropolis. We wish we could say that we're writing to you from a quaint Turkish teahouse with a coffee in one hand and a <del datetime="2014-07-29T14:51:03+00:00">hookah</del> nargile in the other, but we're really just in the lobby of our hostel. We don’t like mixing business and pleasure. (Don't worry, there will be plenty of time for Turkish teahouse-ing and nargile-ing over the next couple days!)

To catch you up, we left Slavonski Brod Saturday morning to hit the highway and cruise through Serbia. Or so we thought. No more than half an hour into the drive we hit traffic, or more accurately, we hit a 10km-long parking lot – precisely the distance to the Serbian border. People were out of their cars, walking down the shoulder, and napping, because as far as the eye could see, not a single car was moving.
 
Oddly enough, most of the cars weren’t Croatian- or Serbian-registered Yugos, as one might expect to see here, but rather, luxury BMWs and Audis with German, along with Turkish decals and bumper stickers. We quickly found out that these cars were occupied by members of the massive Turkish diaspora in Germany, returning to their homeland to celebrate Bayram, the weeklong festival that marks the end of Ramadan. This meant that we’d be stuck in the rush for the next three countries.

Not wanting to waste precious fuel, the Rubikhans decided to put our own car in neutral, and simply push it when we could. And it worked like a charm. For the next four and a half hours – pretty much half a day – we pushed and waited, pushed and waited, pushed and waited, until we reached the border.

With daylight hours already waning, we abandoned our plans to make it to Bulgaria. Instead, we drove (through a couple more traffic jams) to the Serbian city of Niš (pronounced "Nish", not "Nees", which is helpful, since it bears no resemblance whatsoever to the pleasant French city on the Mediterranean). There, after a few dead ends (literal and figurative), we found a hotel willing to take us in. The receptionist (slash owner slash maid slash chief coffee-maker?) even offered us breakfast and a parking spot up on the sidewalk outside. 

Until this point, our only interaction with Serbia, and its people, had been with its traffic-choked roads and utterly loony drivers. So, we were pleasantly surprised by the warm hospitality and helpfulness of the local people we encountered in Niš. Plus, the local beer wasn't half bad! We are beginning to acknowledge the value of modest expections, and we look forward to exploring more of the off-the-beaten-path locales that lie ahead.

We hit the road early the next morning, with our driving goals for the day tempered by the previous day’s frustration. Fortunately, traffic wasn't bad, and we coasted through Eastern Serbia and rejoined our Turkish friends at the mercifully painless Bulgarian border. It was here that Cooper noticed a small sign warning of construction at the major Bulgaria-Turkey border and recommending that cars detour north to the much smaller border in Lesovo. 

Nightmares of border traffic were still fresh in our memory, so 300km later we veered north to the smaller crossing, where we were thankfully met by absolutely no traffic, two Rally teams to chat with, some bird poop for Nick;s shoulder, and a friendly Bulgarian exit guard who laughed us through once we told him our final destination. And it was only 5:00pm. We could make it to Istanbul after all.

So we drove through the twilight and made it to Istanbul with enough energy to meet some other Rallyers for a beer or two in our neighborhood. We looked forward to three nights, and two full days, of recuperation in the city.

Yesterday was our first day away from the car in over a week. We explored Istanbul by foot (for a change) stopping by the Hagia Sofia and Blue Mosque before the heat induced us to yield to the simpler pleasures of tea, beer, deep-fried mussels, lamb kidney, and goat intestines. (Seriously.) That night, we met up with our friend Sera from school who invited us to her home to unwind and catch up. It was exactly what we wanted.
 
We’re crossing our fingers that a garage will be open this afternoon (it’s still Bayram) so we can get someone a little smarter to examine our car before we begin the next legs of our journey. Also in store is a big night out tomorrow with Sera and friends. So let’s see what time we manage to hit the road tomorrow…

Thanks for following, everyone! All of your emails are thoroughly appreciated, and often treasured. So even if we can’t write back with anything resembling punctuality, we love hearing from you. Also, don't forget that you can view our location (updated every ten minutes, as long as our car is moving), right <a href="https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=a9f453c8530592eec" target="_blank">here</a>.

Hobey ho, let’s go!

//The Rubikhans


<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7260529.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1445" />Serbian heavy industry, illuminated by the setting sun.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270557.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1448" />The morning catch in Serbia, featuring Darko, the late Mr. Dragonfly.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270554.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1446" />These guys were driving this horse-drawn cart on the Bulgarian expressway. (Harvard class of 2025?)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270565.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1449" />Bulgaria is the land of sunflowers. Fields of the bright yellow flowers stretch for miles.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270556.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1447" />Is that a MiG-21 in your backyard, or are you just happy to see us? (Spotted somewhere in Bulgaria)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270584.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1450" />The Rubikhans and Team South Afristan, whom we met at the Bulgaria-Turkey border. Cooper was delighted to encounter another Oregonian on the road!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270591.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1451" />The 12km-long queue of lorries waiting to leave Turkey. 

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7270598.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1452" />Benjie enjoys a sunset döner, a few kilometers into Turkey.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7280631.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1453" />Cooper photobombs the New Mosque in Istanbul.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7280655.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1455" />Afternoon prayer at the Blue Mosque.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/P7280642.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1454" />Team photo in front of the Hagia Sophia.






 ]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1444</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-07-29 10:24:01</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-07-29 15:24:01</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>serbulgarstanbul</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>1961</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Patty]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>Pattyscheid@yshoo.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.105.251.63</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-07-29 18:17:28</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-07-29 23:17:28</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA["The value of modest expectations". Now there's a life lesson right there. Love following you guys. Live your map, too. Onward! (Have you named your car or are you waiting for her to reveal her name to you?)]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1406675848.8285229206085205078125;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407125645.929646015167236328125;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>I&#039;m Still Chewing</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/im-still-chewing/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 04:56:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1486</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Salam from Balaken, Azerbaijan! Apologies for the delay between blog posts but we’ve been camping a lot recently and WiFi has been increasingly hard to come by.

Our last post was from Istanbul, from where we departed on Wednesday. The previous day was pleasant: since all of the garages were still closed for Bayram, we took another rest day and some much-needed alone time (hours in the same car and tent can wear on even the closest of friendships). So we went off and found our own cafes to read, write, and drink endless cups of the ubiquitous Turkish black tea. 

That night our friend Sera took us to an amazing tapas (are they still called "tapas" if they're Turkish?) restaurant with a view out over the Bosphorous. A healthy amount of raki, the traditional anise-based Turkish liqueur, accompanied the excellent food. Despite the fact that it's typically diluted with water, this stuff packs a punch. Sera warned us about the hangovers but true to form we ignored her and were consequently in less than top form the next day. I would venture to guess that it was me (Benjie) who got the worst of it, and I spent a few hours feeling vaguely nauseous during a fruitless trip in search of gas for our camping stove to a bizarrely modern shopping mall in suburban Istanbul.

The mood had improved dramatically by the time we pulled off the expressway a few hours later and happened upon another Rally team, the indomitable Americans known as Boyz II Mon, three guys about our age: Charlie, Harry, and Mark. We have been convoying with them since. First night was at a pseudo-campsite by the side of the highway that would have been perfect if not for the occasional freight train that trundled by about a hundred yards away. The next night we made it to the Black Sea and camped by the beach near the little city of Ordu, setting our tents up just in time to take a swim as the sun set. For dinner we had köfte, essentially small spiced hamburger patties, for the fourth meal in a row.

After enjoying a fifth consecutive köfte meal the next morning, we headed for the Georgia line (not the one from the band). The queue to get across the border stretched along the shores of the Black Sea, and we spent about three hours waiting in the late afternoon sun – ultimately a success, given the stories of seven-hour waits we had heard from other Ralliers. We met another team, Ulaan Rouge, a spirited English couple with a spirited bright red car, and decided to add another car to our convoy. The party capital of Georgia, Batumi, lay only 20 minutes past the border, so the eight of us spent the night there. A very strange place for a party capital, we passed various roadside cows before emerging into a city that could best be described as a blend of Las Vegas and Odessa. Huge casinos glittering with neon lights and skyscrapers with built-in Ferris wheels shared streets with run-down tenements. We passed up a strange hotel filled with green lights and various artificial fauna for a wonderful little guesthouse run by a woman named Alika who could not have been more accommodating, even helping to wash the clothes of eight filthy Ralliers.

The following morning we decided to give our car some much-needed love, so we headed to the outskirts of Batumi and found a garage that had four new tires and two steel wheels for us. We also found a friendly Georgian guy who happily translated for us, and helped us find some cheap jerry cans and beaded seat covers. The baker next door insisted on giving us free bread out of his massive cauldron of an oven.

An afternoon of driving led us to a setting sun and a dirt road somewhere in central Georgia where we decided to set up camp for the night. It seemed at first that no one was around, but eventually a stray sheep led us to a small house where we found a woman and her daughter. Communication was difficult, but with hand signals we were able to explain that we were looking for a place to camp. She led us to a perfect spot next to the nearby river, and one of the Ulaan Rougers and I went in search of food and beer while the others made camp.

Later that night the woman’s husband invited us to their house for coffee and watermelon, which we gladly accepted. It was somewhat surreal to be seated in the living room of a family with whom we can only communicate by typing sentences into Google translate, eating melon and watching Lindsay Lohan dubbed on the Georgian version of Disney Channel. I think it is safe to say that Georgia has been our favorite country so far: everyone we met was kind, interested in our adventure, and very helpful despite communication difficulties.

The only trouble with the Georgians is their driving style. Lanes here are wider than usual, and an unofficial, unmarked “third lane” exists between the two normal ones where people pass each other indiscriminately even through curves and hills where they are completely blind. To make matters worse, animals – mainly cows – are to be found lazily wandering around the roadsides unattended and inadvertently walking into traffic. Our convoy has been communicating via walkie-talkie, coordinating bathroom and fuel breaks as well as issuing frequent cow warnings.

This evening we made it to the Azerbaijan border, which, despite what we had heard about long waits and corruption, was relatively painless. We stopped in the first Azeri town we came to and decided to treat ourselves to a night in a hotel with hot showers and shampoo. Unfortunately the only food we could find at such a late hour was pretty much the same thing we have been eating for days now: meat and bread. That brings me to the title of this blog post, “I’m Still Chewing,” which is in fact nearly the case. Tough pork, beef, and lamb with tough, thick bread have sustained us through much of Turkey, Georgia, and now Azerbaijan.

Since our last blog post we have certainly begun to enter the more challenging half of the trip. Communication is difficult and cultural differences are more pronounced. The course of each day is increasingly difficult to predict. Surprises are becoming the norm—but so far, these surprises have been overwhelmingly pleasant. Most people we meet are friendly and interested in where we come from and where we are going, even if they think we’re a bit crazy and don’t understand a word we’re saying.

Our next stop is Azerbaijan’s cosmopolitan capital of Baku. There we will try to find the Turkmenistan embassy to get our visas, which will allow us to get on a ferry across the Caspian Sea. The embassy has no address, and the ferry has no schedule. So stay tuned!

Cheers,

Benjie, Cooper, and Nick

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P7290676.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1468" />Dinner with Sera: the beginning of the end

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P7290690.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1469" />"Raki makes you stronger," they said. "It tastes good, too," they said. Yeah, right.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P7310766.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1471" />Our campsite on the Black Sea

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P7310772.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1472" />Sunset long-exposure

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8010775.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1473" />Waiting to cross into Georgia

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8020832.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1475" />The modest facade of our homely hostel in Batumi

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8020844.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1477" />New tire day at the shop!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8020854.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1478" />The Rubikhans and Timo, the friendly Georgian who drove Nick and Cooper to the market for supplies

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8020857.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1479" />Benjie adorns our car, "Keshav," with the countries on our route

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8020882.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1480" />Badri, a friendly Georgian fisherman plying the waters near our central-Georgian campsite. Cooper spent some time chilling with him on the shore, even though they couldn't really communicate

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8020888.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1481" />Representatives of the Rubikhans, Boyz II Mon, and Ulaan Rouge, with our spontaneous Georgian host(s). (His daughter was too shy to join in the photo)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8030928.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1482" />Keshav makes a high-speed pass (read: 40MPH)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8030937.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1483" />Heading into Azerbaijan

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8030940.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1484" />We ran into a Moldovan team on the far side of the border, and celebrated our successful passage into Azerbaijan with bread and beer




]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1486</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-03 23:56:25</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-04 04:56:25</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>im-still-chewing</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2162</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[David Tanner]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>Datanner@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>74.71.122.74</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-04 20:32:10</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-05 01:32:10</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[You guys rock!!'  Great blog posts, excellent pics and lots of fun tracking your trek.  Keep having fun and stay safe.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407202330.59416103363037109375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407248894.48986911773681640625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Caspian Purgatory (and into the &#039;Stans)</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/caspian-purgatory/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 05:38:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1493</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<em>**We’re currently in Bukhara, Uzbekistan, but we’re so spent from three days of tough driving that we’ll have to save our updates from the past few days for tomorrow (or the next time we have internet). For now, we'll stick to the ferry adventure, but we promise to fill you in on Turkmenistan in no time!**</em>

According to the captain’s log, we last checked in somewhere around the Georgia-Azerbaijan border. We had high hopes that we could fly through Azerbaijan in one day, take care of visa stuff the next day, and hop on a Turkmenistan-bound ferry the same evening. Well, that did not happen.

We made it across Azerbaijan just fine, caravaning with Boyz II Mon up and over the mountains and down to the coastal plain. Our little convoy made it to Baku just in time for a celebratory dinner along the shores of the Caspian. 

Little did we know just how much time we would be spending along the shores of the Caspian.

The next day (Tuesday), we woke up early to head to the ridiculously hidden Turkmen embassy – it was nestled in a nondescript alley in an industrial part of the city, which we could only find thanks to GPS coordinates shared by another Rally team – and began the arduous visa-acquistion process required to enter Turkmenistan. Upon showing up at the embassy, our passport numbers were taken down and we were sent some three kilometers away to a bank where we could make some sort of payment. 

We made it to the bank without problem, and then to a passport photo office, then back to the embassy, where, after we waited in a growing line of other rallyers for nearly an hour, our passports were ceremoniously adorned with the coveted Turkmenistan visa sticker. So far, so good.

Our spirits high, we headed down to the cargo port from where the “ferry” was rumored to depart, in hopes of securing passage that evening. We found the ticket office, but were told to come back at 10AM the next day.

Now this next part of the story is in log form, a medium we’ve chosen since time and duration are integral themes, as you will see:

10:00AM (Wednesday): We show up at the ferry terminal. There's no sign of the woman we spoke with at the ticket office yesterday. Twelve other rally teams slowly join us, and together wait outside the gates. No one (including the young customs officials who saunter around the premises, smoking and cracking jokes amongst themselves), knows much of anything. It’s really hot outside. We seek refuge in the shade of a diesel pipeline.

2:00PM: A local fixer arrives, and assures us that, for the princely sum of $50USD per team, he will help us clear customs and acquire the necessary ferry tickets. As he is the only person at the dock who speaks a word of English, we reluctantly oblige, along with every other team.

3:00PM: All of the rally teams are ushered through the gate and onto a giant shipping dock. Our cars clear customs, and thus are no longer allowed to drive back into Azerbaijan.

5:00PM: The Rubikhans pay their first bribe of the trip when Cooper returns from a quick grocery run and is subsequently forbidden from bringing alcohol through customs. After a tense and lengthy negotiation process, Cooper successfully offers the guards one 12-ounce fruit smoothie in exchange for free passage for his beers.

6:00PM: Benjie joins representatives from a few teams to pick up KFC for us from what is surely the largest KFC in the world. We’re forever grateful.

1:00AM: I (Nick) realize we’re probably not boarding tonight, so I set up my sleeping bag by the car for a grim night’s sleep out on the dock.

2:00AM: Cooper spots a cargo freighter named the Professor Gül approaching the docks. This is the boat we're to take to Turkmenistan. It's already twelve hours late.

2:45AM: The immigration officers promptly wake everyone up and rush us through their office before sending our cars over to our vessel, the aptly named Professor Gül (pronounced ‘Ghoul’).

4:30AM: we’re finally allowed to board the Ghoul, and we park our cars on the very bottom deck of the ship. This becomes important later on. We promptly pass out in the ship’s canteen, since all of the cabins are apparently filled with snoring Azeri sailors.

7:30AM: We’re not-so-gently woken up by a very lound and angry woman, who shows us to our proper cabins through a masterful routine of pointing, yelling, and calling everyone “Francis.” It’s Thursday now. Peering out the windows, we're dismayed to find that the ferry is still in port. So, we take to exploring the noble Ghoul.

Built in the 1980s, the Ghoul has been in service ever since, and it doesn’t seem like a single piece of equipment, furniture, or paint had been replaced since that time. It is a hulking, rusted relic of the golden age of Caspian Sea shipping (based on our extensive knowledge about the history of Caspian Sea shipping).

But nothing is off limits, and so we wander from the bow to the stern, up and down decks, and even into the emergency escape vessels. The 30-odd rallyers share the ship with the crew and several other passengers, eating our stored food, drinking our stored vodka and convivially passing the time – and there is certainly time to pass because…

5:15PM: The ferry finally leaves port, over 31 hours after we arrived at the terminal. A massive cheer erupts from the ralliers. 

1:00PM (Friday): The ferry docks in Turkmenbashi, and we are immediately shooed down to our cars in the bowels of the ship by the same nameless lady who unceremoniously woke us up the previous morning.

Remember how I said our cars were at the very bottom? This is important because we must now wait for every single truck to offload before we can even think of getting off the ship. So we impatiently linger in the hot, stuffy, cargo hull – chugging water and trying to move as little as possible. Occassionally, we sneak up to the upper decks for some fresh air, but the crazy "Francis" lady inevitably spots us and corrals us back down into the hull. 

4:30PM: The door opens and we’re finally able to drive off the boat – and right into the Turkmenistan border!

The Turkmen immigration process is the most absurd and horrible bureaucratic nightmare we've ever encountered. It deserves its own 16-step subsection. (I know you may be bored reading all of this, but consider it part of the experience. It’s almost like you’re here with us!):

1) Go one-by-one to a booth where your passports are returned (the ship had held onto them)

2) Go to a 2nd booth to pay the $12 fee to get your passport back, acquire receipt

3) Return to the first booth to hand in receipt, receive indecipherable random form

4) Take indecipherable form to an office, receive another indecipherable form

5) Take all forms to a 2nd office, get something stamped

6) Take forms to a 3rd office, get another stamp

7) Go around building to a 4th office where a man tells you he needs six drivers at a time in order to bestow yet another indecipherable form

8) After waiting for five more drivers, get forms and head to Ticket Office to trade in form for another indecipherable form

9) Take new form to 2nd booth (from before!), pay $158 for some reason or another, receive another receipt

10) Take all forms to 5th office to get signed, stamped, whatevered by someone who looks somewhat more official. Receive new indecipherable form

11) Take newest form to 6th office to get stamped

12) Take same form to 7th office to get stamped and signed

13) Return to 5th office to turn in form

14) Fill out customs declaration

15) Get car searched by military officer in green forest camo (because no one told him that Turkmenistan is entirely desert)

16) Turn in one of the dozen or so accumulated forms to man at gate, revel in your freedom

9:30PM: we leave the border and promptly find a hotel, restaurant, and a round of cold beers. It is Friday night after all...

More to come, as soon as we find the time (and internet) to upload another post!

Nick, Cooper, Benjie

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8040945.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="675" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1494" />Azerbaijan, in a nutshell

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8050975.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1497" />Main entrance to the Turkmenistan embassy

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8050992.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1498" />Old City, Baku

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8040967.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="675" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1496" />Baku skyline. (Not pictured: the world's second-tallest flagpole)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8061031.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1500" />Lounging on the dock, waiting (indefinitely) for the ferry

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8071045.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1502" />Minutes before we loaded our cars onto the Professor Gül

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8071055.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1503" />The next morning: still in port

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8071057.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1504" />Inspecting the escape vessels

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8071067.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1507" />At long last, we leave Baku behind!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8071093.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1508" />The Rubikhans pose on the Gül's afterdeck

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8081138.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1509" />Approaching Turkmenbashi

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8081156.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1510" />The Turkmenistan national fleet]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1493</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-12 00:38:42</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-12 05:38:42</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>caspian-purgatory</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2823</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Barbara Seiders]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>barbara.seiders@eigenseide.net</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.onehundredyearhorizons.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>71.80.156.80</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-12 02:14:35</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-12 07:14:35</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Great update. Sounds like the Rally is being a typical Rally, spending more time waiting to travel or to cross borders than actually traveling! I've got to say as a world traveling '77, the picture of one of you guys at the entrance to the Turkmenistan Embassy in a D'mouth shirt made me a little misty eyed! Also, nice hammock! Safe travels, gentlemen!]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407827675.4292790889739990234375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407948064.961761951446533203125;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2888</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Peggy]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>pegtan5@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>74.71.122.74</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-12 15:12:15</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-12 20:12:15</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I am trying to decide if I should laugh or cry for you?.  This is quite the blog....as always, extremely well written, but YUCK!!  I bet more than once during the past few days you questioned your decision to spend your summers Crossing the Rubikhan?!?!?  I mean you could be working in some 2/ 7 job in NYC wearing  ties and jackets and .....oh wait...at least one of you will be doing that soon.  :)  
Get some rest and know your followers are cheering you along every step of the way.  Keep enjoying.  We love your reports and photos.  xo  Aunt Peggy]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407874335.47818088531494140625;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407948108.61190700531005859375;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2889</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Peggy]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>pegtan5@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>74.71.122.74</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-12 15:15:17</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-12 20:15:17</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[24/7 job....excuse the many typos.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>2888</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407874517.7832028865814208984375;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407948109.664658069610595703125;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2900</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[datanner@gmail.com]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>datanner@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>208.252.31.131</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-12 17:24:22</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-12 22:24:22</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Surreal!!  A lifetime of adventures and stories in just a couple of months.  Keep the stories and pictures coming and enjoy the 'stans!!  David]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407882262.8880360126495361328125;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407948192.00629901885986328125;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The Legend of Keshav Pothole: An Abusive Relationship</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/keshav-pothole/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2014 18:10:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1535</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[They say that there is no such thing as perfect conditions for writing. Well, I’m writing to you now from a small shack on the side of a rural highway, about halfway between Bukhara and Samarkand. We’re out of gas. We didn’t plan to be out of gas – this isn’t one of those out-of-gas moments where you’re almost out of gas, see a gas station and think you can press on to the next one but you don’t make it. No – we started today in Bukhara with 2/3 of a tank. And we haven’t passed a single open gas station since.

There seems to be some sort of fuel shortage in Uzbekistan – closed petrol stations litter the side of the road. So we’ve been forced to try our luck on the petrol black market. Benjie is currently in a local’s car, en route to who-knows-where, armed with two empty water bottles to bring back who-knows-what. But more on that later. For now, let me catch you up on the past few days:

The Turkmenbashi-Ashgabat "highway" (a generous use of the term) was fine for the first couple hundred kilometers (we've taken to the metric system), save for the occasional rough patch. We tore across the stark Karakum Desert as fast as our steed would carry us, with nothing but camels to keep us company. Then we hit the war zone. We’re unsure if an actual war had taken place on this 150km stretch of “highway,” but it sure seemed like it. The potholes were a little smaller than our car, or about the same size as Benjie’s driving hubris.

It was on these roads that our steed earned its name, and it is with great excitement that we can now introduce to you the Tandoori Terror, the Massala Menace, the Vindaloo Vehicle: Keshav Pothole! Indeed, we've chosen to memorialize our late teammate by naming our car after him. There's one catch, however – we've already determined that our car is a female. Sorry, Shav.

Just when we thought we couldn’t take the brutal roads any longer, Ashgabat’s gaudy, opulent tentacles reached out in the form of a freshly paved four-lane highway, replete with gold and white fencing and shimmering statues of the Dear Leader. The bridges were still crap though.

So we coasted into Ashgabat, a city best described as equal parts Las Vegas and Pyongyang. The buildings were white marble with liberal amounts of gold trim. Pictures and statues of Turkmenbashi (literally, "Leader of the Turkmen) and his successor, the equally self-righteous  Gurbanguly Berdimuhamedow (say that ten times fast) were everywhere, as were police. Benjie’s attempt to film our drive into the city center was hampered by a distinct fear that a police officer would pull us over, take the camera, and unceremoniously smash it onto the ground (this didn’t happen but they really don’t like people taking photos).

After a night’s rest in one of the more Soviet establishments in town, we attempted to fix our roof rails, which had slid forward about six inches at some point in Pothole Land, as well as our roof box, which had by now lost both of its hydraulic arms as well as one of its two hinges. We soon realized that our efforts had caused more harm than good, so we duct taped the box in place and hit the road for another day of potholes. 

The Rubikhans slowly navigated their way out of Ashgabat (no thanks to three inexplicably closed highways), and eventually wound up on more beautiful tarmac – the gaudy tentacles of Ashgabat extending out towards Mary, our destination for the night. Cautiously optimistic that the tarmac would continue for quite some time, we were pleasantly surprised to make it a solid 100km out of the city before returning to Pothole Land. So we grueled through it, our suspension shaking and groaning, our roof box rattling, and our teeth chattering. We fought off the 114-degree desert heat with warm water and open windows.

And we were rewarded for our toilsome efforts, for our accommodations in Mary had the one thing we needed most but didn't expect to find in the desert: a swimming pool. And we swam, and we feasted on “Hot Amerikan Pizza,” and we slept, and we woke up to try to fix the roof box again, and we broke it even more, and we applied even more duct tape, because why not? And we drove off toward the Uzbekistan border.

Despite Turkmenistan's reputation as a hermit kingdom second only in isolationism to North Korea, the people we encountered proved to be wonderfully hospitable and friendly. On one occassion, a fellow driver even got out of his car at a traffic light to gift us some tasty bread! And countless cars honk and wave at us as they (inevitably) pass us on the highway. It seems as though everyone we've encountered on this tremendous journey is willing us to succeed. And without their support, we wouldn't have made it this far.

The roads from Mary were thankfully not terrible, and we made it to the border by early afternoon. We suffered a bit of PTSD at the Turkmen exit border (only about five pointless stations this time) and drove on to Uzbekistan, where the border guards had big guns and bigger senses of humor.

We had been dreading the thorough search of the car that other teams had encountered at the Uzbek border, but the guards just had us open a couple doors, tried on our sunglasses, and waved us into their country, telling us to bring girls next time. Maybe not, given how we smell right now.

After hours upon hours of bleak desert terrain, arriving in Bukhara was like dream. We dropped our bags at the hotel (which had, along with many other hotels in the city, incidentally lost all electricty), and then meandered through the carefully preserved old city, surrounding ourselves in a buzzing maze of sandstone mosques, turquoise minarets, and lush courtyards. It's no wonder that this city is heralded as one of the most beautiful in Eurasia. It hardly felt real.

We presently decided to exchange some money on the ubiquitous “black market,” where a US dollar goes for ~2800som. Since 1000som is the largest denomination in circulation, exchanging $20 dollars gave each of us stacks of 56 bills. I hadn’t felt this rich since my brother landed on my Boardwalk hotel in Monopoly. It was so much money, I couldn’t fit it in a lunchbox (Michael “BDM” Parets, 2011).

Benjie here, taking over the narration (with Cooper adding serial commas and supplementary commentary). Fortunately, at this point I was wearing cargo shorts, giving me the perfect place to keep my stacks of money. We decided to go to dinner and were on our way there when we saw two guys looking at us quizzically; after a few seconds we realized that they were the Austrian ralliers we had met all the way back at the London launch party. One of them had given me a stamped and punched “One-way ticket to Adventureland,” and lo and behold we meet them here, most certainly in the heart of Adventureland. An amazing coincidence, but just one of many occasions on which we have chanced upon another Rally team and been instantly and happily united by our shared quest – to me, this is one of the coolest parts of the Rally experience.

After an excellent breakfast from our lovely hosts the next morning, we set off for Samarkand in high spirits. Unfortunately, as Nick mentioned, these were quickly crushed. Potholes and bumps everywhere. Dozens of closed gas stations – the only open one we saw had a line that stretched over a hundred yards. And then our roof rack, which has been slowly deteriorating, finally cracked and the lid to our front compartment flew off like a leaf in the breeze. Fortunately, no one was behind us, and so we simply pulled off the road and stuffed our tent and sleeping bags into the car, bringing our packing jigsaw puzzle to an entirely new level.

It was also at this point that gas became a serious problem, and we decided to pull off by the small shack/repair shop where Nick began writing this blog post. Eventually, we communicated with the proprietors that we wanted petrol, and agreed on a price for the 6.5 liters we could carry in our empty plastic water bottles. So I rode off with our generous providers, a father and his son who had outfitted their Soviet-era Lada Riva with a set of massive Pioneer speakers that blasted Uzbek dance music at a nearly intolerable volume. We went to the next town over where a nice lady filled the water bottles out of a massive black plastic drum next to her shop, and we were off to Samarkand!

Generally thought to be the pearl of Central Asia, Samarkand is a mystically beautiful city that was once the most powerful point on the Silk Road and an important center of Islamic learning. Its central square, known as the Registan, is bordered on three sides by medressas (Islamic theological schools) that were built beginning in the 1400s. Because we arrived too late to see them last night, Cooper and I woke up at 7am this morning to have a look, and were rewarded with an incredible experience.

Since the buildings didn't open to the public until 8:am, hardly anyone was around: just a couple of policemen and a few babushkas sweeping the square, which was bathed in morning light. The exquisite geometric patterns that adorn the ancient buildings glowed in soft hues of turquoise and green and gold. For 12,000 som – a little over four dollars – a policeman allowed us to clandestinely climb the narrow spiral steps up one of the minarets from which we could observe the whole scene from above. Words can’t do it justice, so have a look at the pictures below, but without a doubt it was one of the most remarkable places I have ever seen. 

After buying more black market gasoline in Samarkand – this time, with the help of our English-speaking B&B host – we set off for the sprawling capital of Tashkent. The roads proved to be much better than we’d seen in previous days, so we made good progress and arrived with plenty of time to explore a bit and have a massive dinner of various unnamed Uzbek delicacies which may or may not wreak havoc on our stomachs tomorrow. But they were sure tasty. We rounded out the night with a couple of beers in the square next to our hotel, where some local kids engaged us in a riveting conversation consisting of random English words for things they saw: Tomato! Food! Refrigerator! Instagram! Sexy!

Tomorrow (assuming we can find enough gas) we are off to Osh, the largest city in southern Kyrgyzstan. We are told that the roads are decent, and are fervently hoping that this is the case – because Vishnu knows, Keshav Pothole could use a break.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8091173.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1521" />KP on the road to Ashgabat

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8091170.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1520" />Our first encounter with roving camels

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8091183.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1522" />Ostentatious mosque/government building on the outskirts of Ashgabat

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8101194.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1524" />"Mom, I'm five kilometers from Iran!"

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8111215.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1526" />Ridin' dirty on the donkey cart (note the iPod)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8111250.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1530" />Dusk in Bukhara

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8111236.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1528" />One of the countless mosques/madrassas in Bukhara's old city

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8111245.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1529" />Team photo in the window

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8111232.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1527" />Old city road

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8111260.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1531" />Benjie flaunts his money (worth about $16)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131287.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1540" />The Registan, in Samarkand, in the early morning light

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131336.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1536" />Uzbek women inside one of the Registan's three primary madrassas

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131315.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1533" />The Ulugh Beg Madrassa (the eldest of the three), viewed from a minaret

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131343.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1537" />Intricate tilework on the ceiling of the Ulugh Beg Madrassa

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131293.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1532" />Benjie ogles the Registan. (Note the kimono, which was loaned to him by our kind hostess, who was worried that he'd get cold)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131335.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1534" />New friends in Samarkand

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8131357.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1538" />The Tashkent circus. Tomorrow, Kyrgyzstan!



]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1535</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-13 13:10:58</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-13 18:10:58</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>keshav-pothole</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>2959</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Patty]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>pattyscheid@yahoo.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.105.251.63</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-13 13:48:04</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-13 18:48:04</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[So good to hear from you. Your post made me anxious, tense, happy and amused. And I cringed at the 5k from the Iran border shot - but that was the point of it, right?  The other photos: terrific!]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1407955684.7256629467010498046875;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Brief Update from Almaty</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/brief-update-from-almaty/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 03:22:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1546</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Greetings from Almaty, Kazakhstan, where we arrived late last night. Since our last dispatch, we’ve enjoyed three truly incredible days of driving. First, we descended into Uzbekistan’s fecund Fergana Valley, crossed the border into Kyrgyzstan, and enjoyed a wonderful homecooked meal in the region's cultural capital, Osh. Then, we headed north into the foothills of the Tien Shan mountain range, and camped by a massive, emerald-blue reservoir. And yesterday, we continued our climb through the Tien Shan, passing over two 10,000-foot passes before descending into Bishkek (where Cooper will be living next year), crossing into Kazakhstan, and bombing across the motorway to Almaty in time for a late dinner and a round of cold beers.

We’re eager to hit the road this morning, and so we don’t have time for a full update, but we’ll provide you with a full rundown of the past few days as soon as we have wifi again. Remember, you can check out our <a href="https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=a9f453c8530592eec" target="_blank">live-tracking map</a> to view our progress. Below are a couple photos to whet your appetite for the full post.

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8141394.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1547" />Chaikhana lunch in central Uzbekistan

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8141405.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1548" />Tearing across the Fergana Valley

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8161498.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1549" />Yurts in the Tien Shan Mountains

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8161481.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1554" />Benjie and Cooper celebrate the high altitude mark of the trip (somewhere around 12,000ft), while Nick ogles a rock

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8161532.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1550" />Late-night driver swap, somewhere in Kazakhstan]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1546</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-16 22:22:19</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-17 03:22:19</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>brief-update-from-almaty</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>It Was the Best of Roads, It Was the Worst of Roads</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/best-roads-worst-roads/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2014 03:53:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1561</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Hello from the Siberian plain! Nick here. We’ve made it to Barnaul, Russia, having successfully navigated the famous Kyrgyz peaks and the infamous Kazakh steppe. Since it’s been a while since we’ve treated you to a full update (Tashkent methinks), let’s backtrack a bit to fill you in. Unfortunately, Russia has blacklisted our website (we can't imagine why...), and so we're using a proxy service to post this. As a result, we can't upload any photos. We'll add them as soon as possible.

There are several segments of this journey that I expected to be beautiful—the Croatian coast, Istanbul, and Bukhara to name a few. Then there are those moments that catch you totally by surprise. The landscapes and cities that we’d overlooked and subsequently took our breath away. These moments are what the Rally is all about. And the drive into the Fergana Valley was one of those moments. 

Mostly known as a bastion of Islamic fundamentalism and for the tragic massacre of 2005, we were traversing the Fergana simply as a means to get between Tashkent and Osh, gateway to Kyrgyzstan and the towering Tian Shan mountains. Entering the valley from Tashkent required several police checkpoints and one massive mountain pass. Keshav Pothole chugged up and up and up until we finally got a glance behind us and were met with a stunning vista of the valley behind us.

Working our way through the pass, we stumbled upon a traditional mountainside teahouse and spread out on the carpeted benches to nibble on shashlyk and enjoy the mountain air. Cooper taught Benjie and me the traditional way to pour tea—which was not, as I had hoped, onto Cooper’s head. Our bellies full, we descended into the valley and sped our way towards Osh, making it to the border just before it closed for the evening.

We had just checked in to our bazaar-adjacent hotel and were retrieving our bags while chatting with a local family who had parked by us. Next thing we know, we were sitting in their nearby apartment, having been invited to dinner. We had experienced some pretty exceptional Central Asian hospitality—local people going way out of their way to help us out and welcome us to their towns—but this took the cake. Cooper was beyond ecstatic, presumably realizing that he would soon spend a full year immersed in the pervasive generosity and kindness that are central tenants of Kyrgyz culture.

The reason for our invitation was an upcoming test. The younger son was taking English in university and was unprepared for a major exam, two weeks away. We like to think our conversation helped give him a little more comfort with the language, but my mind was on the delicious potatoes and watermelon we slowly polished away as we talked. What a way to be welcomed to a new country.

Cooper and Benjie took to the bazaar the next morning while I took advantage of the finally cool weather to go for a run. We said goodbye to Osh just before noon and pushed headword into the mountains, stopping to link up with a few more Ralliers, one of whom graciously noted that a lug nut on our front wheel was missing. Thanks for the heads up!

Several hours of progressively higher foothills brought us to an emerald blue reservoir with a swimming area and café. Needless to say, we stopped for a couple hours of swimming and eating, which culminated in the loquacious owner bringing forth a bottle of vodka to drink with us. The non-drivers toasted with him as we endured detailed descriptions of his business plan and the tourism industry (Allen family—picture a Kyrgyz Sharky). 

We left the reservoir and wound our way up the side of a deep and narrow canyon before darkness set and the three teams set up camp in the backyard of a roadside café, where we were quickly joined by a fourth team who had spotted our ubiquitous Mongol Rally stickers from the highway.

The mountains on the next day’s drive cannot, should not, and will not be described in words. Cooper’s pictures will surely tell a better story (our update from Almaty had a sneak peek—peak?—as well).

We thoroughly enjoyed the stunning scenery and good road, taking pictures, whipping out the drone for a thin-air flight, and mostly just staring out the windows in wonder. We descended into Bishkek early enough to stock up on camping supplies, grab a meal and push across the Kazakh border to Almaty. 

It felt weird spending so little time in the city that Cooper is two weeks away from calling home, but it was early in the day and we had heard bad things about the roads in Kazakhstan so we wanted a head start. Also Cooper will be spending enough time there soon enough—all’s fair in love and rallying. 

From Almaty we gritted our teeth and trekked north, ready for the 1,100km of potholed roads we had heard so much about. Suburbs quickly gave way to vast nothingness—just the rolling hills and massive grass plain of the steppe—and the roads were indeed bad. In typical Central Asian fashion, a brand new but not-quite –open highway paralleled our route as we bumped and rattled along before the highway disappeared all together and the roads got…better? They weren’t good by any standards, but they were better than we expected and by the time the sun was setting, we had made surprisingly good progress. 

We pulled off onto a dirt track and found a creek-side grove of trees in which to pitch our tent. As the sky turned orange, we meandered out of the grove to watch the sun set over an endless ocean of grass—the horizon line perfectly straight, as if over an actual sea.

We awoke early the next day and traversed the tranquil steppe on surprisingly ok roads (with the occasional nasty surprise) until, just as we had started to look for places to camp, we were passed by none other than our Austrian friends, Team Adventureland! This was our fifth time running into Alexander and Niklas and the first since Bukhara, where we had had dinner with them a week before.

So we went to the next town, picked up some necessities (water and beer) and pulled off to camp in a field a few hundred kilometers from the highway. But we cooked, and we drank our beers, and we happily chatted until the late hour of 9:30, when we retreated to our tents to prepare for one last day of Kazakhstan.

We said goodbye to the Austrians at the campsite—they were off to see the Polygon, a defunct nuclear testing zone from the Soviet era where the leftover radiation still plagues the residents of nearby Semey.

We were also going through Semey and were met with 150km of almost-finished highway. In the starkest road quality contrast of the entire rally to date, we alternated between spanking new tarmac and a horrible concoction of rocks-that are-a-little-too-big-to-be-considered-gravel and sneaky, vicious pot holes. 

So overall we made decently good time, and worked our way to the Russian border, where getting out of Kazakhstan turned out to be a much bigger pain than getting into Russia. So long Central Asia!

I write to you now from the backseat as we speed our way up first-rate Russian highways to Barnaul, where we hope to post this update, but not before getting a much-needed shower. 

Thanks for indulging us by reading, writing and following our GPS map! Can’t wait to update you from Mongolia itself—aiming to reach the border tomorrow! It feels like the true rally is just beginning.

]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1561</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-19 22:53:30</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-20 03:53:30</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>best-roads-worst-roads</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[it-was-the-best-of-roads-it-was-the-worst-of-roads]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>3494</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Peggy Tanner]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>Pegtan5@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>70.208.91.95</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-20 06:11:22</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-20 11:11:22</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I know Ima and Papa are filled with relief as they read this blog. I, on the other hand, am starting to feel sad as these blogs are  beautifully written and transport me right into your back seat. What an adventure. I am jealous. 

I look forward to seeing the photos and hearing about Mongolia and the finish line. Hope you win a trophy. LOL. 

SOP finishes its session on Thursday. It's been tenser than normal, but ending well.  There has been a ton of positive press. And .... Andrew loehse's book comes out this week and the NY Post wrote a terrible piece about it this morning. The article was filled with inaccuracies and was a lot less fun to read than your blog!!  Robbie is studying for finals and writing papers (just incase you are feeling cramped, hot and smelly and need to feel schadenfreude).  

We are super excited to welcome Nick to NYC. It's beginning to feel real as you head to Mongolia and your parents put down a deposit on a apartment!!  

To Russia with Love.....back in the USSR (I am dating myself)!  Enjoy

Peggy]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1408533082.856401920318603515625;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1409331255.2582399845123291015625;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Kazakhstan and Russia: Photo Edition</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/kazakhstan-and-russia/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 10:05:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1575</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Below are a handful of photos from our weeklong passage across the Kazakh steppe and Russian taiga. Next up: a detailed breakdown (pun entirely intended) of our time in Mongolia!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8171570.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1567" />Team photo from our second night in Kazakhstan. (Taken by a kind goat who happened by)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8171565.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1566" />The Tandoori Terror (our undersized car) and the Cathedral of Comfort (our oversized tent) – a match made in heaven

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8171576.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1568" />Sunset over the steppe

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8171545.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1565" />One of the many fascinating roadside city/region signs we passed in Kazakhstan

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8181591.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1569" />Keshav Pothole earns her stripes

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8181610.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1571" />A lonely train, somewhere in Kazakhstan

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8181624.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1573" />Camping with our Austrian friends from <a href="http://adventureland-mongolia.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">Team Adventureland</a>

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8181602.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1570" />Cooper's shameless steppe selfie

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8201631.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1574" />A cosy Russian dacha in the Altai Republic

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8201644.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1576" />KP flies by in the rain

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211674.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1586" />The Altai Mountains (sort of)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211664.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1578" />One of the spectacular Russian motorways

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211656.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1577" />The Rubikhans are in Russia!


]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1575</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-29 05:05:25</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-29 10:05:25</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>kazakhstan-and-russia</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[kazakhstan-and-russia-photo-edition]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Mongolia, Part I</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/mongolia-part-i/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2014 05:10:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1589</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Mongolia, Mongolia. Where to begin?

We’ve decided to split this country into two party-sized posts (as opposed to one king-sized post), since our traversal of Mongolia was really the culminating stage of our journey. This is Part I; Part II will be posted tomorrow. We’re just trying to keep you entertained.

Anyway, we (Nick and Cooper) will pick up where we left off: in Barnaul, Russia. 

After stocking up on supplies (read: an assortment of commie-brand instant noodle packets and cans of something that turned to be anything BUT tuna), we hit the good Russian motorway and made for the Altai Mountains. The smooth, winding mountain roads gave us little trouble – in fact, they were some of the nicest roads we’d encountered in weeks, and they offered incredible alpine views, to boot. So, we turned up the volume on Cooper’s Tuvan throat singing collection and tumbled along at a heady 80km/h. It was almost as though we’d suddenly returned to Europe (and, depending on how you define Russia geographically, perhaps we did).  

After a day and a half on the road, the mountains abruptly crumbled back into the endless steppe, and before long, we reached the border – well, the Russian exit border, that is. Before actually entering Mongolia, we had to pass through 20km of no-man’s land, occupied solely by some goats of ambiguous nationality, some blubbery beaver-like marmots skittering about (they’ll make a return appearance), and a man bizarrely mowing a small patch of grass next to the road. Also in no-man’s land, Keshav “the KP Cruiser” Pothole’s odometer hit 100,000km, and the road turned from asphalt to dirt.

What began as a relatively routine border crossing (“passport, mister!” “driver here, passenger there, mister!”) took a turn for the Mongolian when a border agent asked us to sell him some petrol from our jerry can. Since he still had Nick's passport and unstamped documents in hand, we were in no position to refuse. He proceeded to explain to us, while carelessly smoking a cigarette inches from the fuel, that he needed the petrol to go hunting after work. We asked if we could come along. And so began one of the strangest side-trips of our adventure. 

The border official told us to wait for him in a small restaurant down the road, and 40 minutes later, while were feasting on buuz (delicious Mongolian dumplings), our friend rolled up in a souped-up Prius, accompanied by another border guard and a .22 rifle. We piled into the back seat and sped off, abandoning the dirt path (or “highway,” as our maps labeled it) to careen up a grass hill in search of the large Tarbagan marmots that burrow in the hillsides. Spotting one particularly plump beast scuttling around in the rocks, our hosts chased it into its hole, pulled up nearby – utilizing the lethal silence of our hybrid cruiser – and trained the rifle out the passenger window. Thirty seconds later, the marmot peeped his little head up for a looksie, and was immediately nailed between the eyes. While the shooter whooped and hollered, his friend leapt out of the car, ran over to the hole, and reaching down, grabbed the twitching marmot by its tail and flung it a full 10 feet into the air. Once the poor beast was sufficiently dead, our hosts bagged it up, and stuck it in the trunk.

Ten minutes and one marmot later, and we were speeding back across the hills and toward our car, while our new friends regaled us with glorious tales of wolf-hunts with AK-47s and marksmanship competitions with the Russian guards. By all accounts, it had been a successful outing: our friends had procured their dinner for the night, and we had the somewhat reassuring knowledge that the Toyota Prius was considered a suitable off-roading vehicle. 

As the sun began to set, we serendipitously ran into the English and Northern Irish guys with whom we had caravanned through Kyrgyzstan, as well as a Danish and an Israeli team. After driving about 20km from the border, we set up camp in the center of a massive valley with nothing but nothing in every direction. The stars were stunning.

We celebrated our entrance into Mongolia with champagne (sabred with a poop trowel) and an encounter with a local guy on a motorcycle who insisted on drinking all of our alcohol, wrestling Jon, one of the Danes (who sadly lost), and singing (err, shouting) traditional folk songs. Oddly, our nameless Mongolian friend insisted on wearing his motorcycle helmet the entire time he was with us. 

The next day delivered our first taste of Mongolian off-roading. While the dirt roads, river crossings, and the Danes’ 1984 Fiat 127 hindered our progress, we had a blast tearing across the rugged steppe, dangling out the car windows with wanton disregard for our personal safety, and hooting and hollering like we were young again. Sometimes, the dirt paths would diverge, and our entire convoy would barrel ahead five cars abreast. Though our speed rarely exceeded 40km/h, it felt like we were flying over the dirt. This is what Mongolia was all about. This is what we’d traveled all this way to experience.

At one point, a particularly muddy mud pit rendered the Israelis immobile. Fortunately, a local jeep, commandeered by a man who was almost certainly drunk, arrived on the spot, and offered to tow them out from behind. The driver got a bit overzealous, and yanked the Israeli’s Renault Kangoo across the mud like a water skier, while Stav, the driver, helplessly jamming on the brakes and handbrake and bellowing “stop!”, before the tow hook mercifully snapped. We all had a good laugh. The jeep driver offered to tow the rest of us, and we quickly declined. Onward we trekked, our clothes a little mudder and our cars a little creakier. As the sun began to set, we pitched camp at the foot of a steep slope, the hillside offering solid protection from the wind.

We got an early start the next morning, hoping to recoup some of the mileage (kilometerage?) that we’d lost the previous day. For hours, we sped through the hills and mountains on interwoven dirt paths. The driving experience itself was akin to backcountry skiing: we carefully picked our lines to avoid bumpy roads and loose boulders, weaving left and right around tightly banked turns, power sliding over loose sand, and literally flying over small crests in the road. It was wild fun, unlike any driving we’d encountered previously. Frankly, we were ‘shocked’ (foreshadowing) that our little Alto could handle the abuse.  

Unfortunately, however, our roof box (which, you may recall, began to disintegrate in Turkmenistan) had plans of its own. Somewhere near Khovd, a nasty, well-concealed bump sent us completely airborne, and the rough landing launched the roof box forward, so that it dangled precariously over the windshield. We happily poured the rest of our jerry can into the tank, strapped Cooper’s bag to the roof, and stuffed what we could into the trunk. To the rest, we said good riddance and gave it a new home in the middle of the steppe.

By late afternoon, our convoy arrived in Khovd. We were dirty, exhausted, and still slightly buzzing from the adrenaline high. While we refueled and restocked, we shared stories about our favorite sections of road, craziest maneuvers, and preferred driving playlists. We pressed on, and were treated to 200km of brand new tarmac leaving town. (Mongolia is in the midst of an extensive project to pave the entire east-west highway. While the project is supposed to be complete by 2020, the only proof of progress is this stretch leading out of Khovd, and a similar stretch leading out of Altai, which we’d hit a few days later.) Our suspensions and constitutions were immensely grateful for the reprieve.

The tarmac eventually ended, however, and was sadly replaced by the horrible washboard gravel of an under-construction motorway. We shaked and rattled over the gruesome bumps for several kilometers before we noticed a series of trails winding about on either side. When Mongolians don’t like a road, they create their own. So, we departed from the main road, made for the the side paths, and zigzagged through an immense valley plain until a setting sun induced us to camp. Everyone slept well that night.

And so concludes Part I. In Part II, you’ll hear about our next five days in Mongolia, including our final push to the finish line (spoiler alert: we finished).

We want to extend our enormous gratitude for the ridiculous amount of support we’ve received over the past seven weeks and the year of preparation before. The Mongol Rally has been a huge part of our lives since we started scheming last August, and it literally has been our lives since we touched down in London a month and a half ago. We’re amazed how an adventure that took us one third of the way around the world and thousands of miles from home could bring us so much closer with so many of the people we love and care about. We’ve reconnected with the countless friends and family members who have reached out with their enthusiastic support (and obscure restaurant recommendations in Olgii – the chicken was delicious, by the way). We can’t wait to see you all and finally catch up face to face. 

While the Rally has made all three of us acutely aware of just how vast the world actually is, it has also reminded us that our network of loved ones is equally immense. And that’s something we’ll remember long after we fly home.

-The Rubikhans

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211682.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1591" />Our final border crossing

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211688.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1593" />Hunting marmots out the window of a Prius

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211685.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1592" />Dinner?

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211692.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1595" />Curious Mongolian children near the border

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211693.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1596" />The long and not-so-winding road to Ulaanbaatar (extremely limited edition tarmac variant)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8211690.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1594" />The endless Mongolian steppe

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221706.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1600" />Our campsite on the first night

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/DSC_0020.jpg" alt="DSC_0020" width="1200" height="798" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1624" />Milky Way x Comfort Cathedral collaboration

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221708.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1601" />A young horseman who paid our camp a visit

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8241855.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1620" />The English, Danish, and Northern Irish teams bounce along through the desert

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8231826.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1610" />Celebrating our first day of off-road driving

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221732.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1603" />Cooper points at the local fauna (part 1)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221720.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1602" />Cooper  points at the local fauna (part 2)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221774.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1604" />KP takes on a mountain stream

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221796.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1605" />Benjie and Nick ponder the long road ahead

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/DSC_0023.jpg" alt="DSC_0023" width="1200" height="798" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1616" />Rob climbs the window out for a better view

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221808.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1623" />The Israelis' Kangoo, stuck in the mud

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8221807.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1607" />KP, after a good wallow

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8231822.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1609" />Cooper's fashionable attempt to overcome the dust

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P82318311.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1619" />Nick "inspects" a post-roofbox KP

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/DSC_0035.jpg" alt="DSC_0035" width="1200" height="798" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1617" />Our Danish friends, just hanging out

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8231842.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1612" />A gang of Bactrian camels in the shadow of the mountains

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8231844.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1613" />The full convoy, just outside Khovd

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8241873.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1619" />KP, dwarfed by the massive scale of the Mongolian steppe]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1589</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-30 00:10:07</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-30 05:10:07</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>mongolia-part-i</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Mongolia, Part II</title>
		<link>http://crossingtherubikhan.com/mongolia-part-ii/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2014 10:20:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[buzkashi]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://crossingtherubikhan.com/?p=1636</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Benjie here, resuming our Mongolian narrative from the middle of the interminably long valley between Khovd and Altai that essentialized our fourth day in the country. This may have been the most frustrating stretch of our drive through Mongolia: the landscape was flat and repetitive, offering no distraction from the torturous, obscenity-inducing washboard road we were forced to drive on. Roads like these wreak havoc on cars’ suspension systems, and while ours remained intact (for the moment) our Danish friends had frequent problems including one harrowing moment when their left rear suspension spring cracked entirely and busted through the frame of their car, allowing the person in the back seat to see straight through to the road below. 

After ten hours and several stops for MacGyver-esque repairs to the Danes’ Fiat, we emerged from the Valley of Death and climbed over some small mountains onto a beautiful green plateau that puts the ubiquitous Windows desktop picture to shame. We careened along, thrilled to be back on pleasant dirt roads. The skiing metaphor mentioned in our last post is entirely apt: some lines are better than others, and I would alternately cackle as we flew by other cars or mutter oaths after making a bad choice. Our English friends, Rob and Jack, were a little over-zealous and gunned it over the plateau too fast to notice a massive pothole in front of them that stopped their car dead in its tracks and caused their roof rack to fly a good ten feet further. Two days, two roof racks gone—but hey, it’s Mongolia, that’s what’s supposed to happen.

Eventually we reached the edge of the plateau where the little town of Altai unfolded below us, its bright multicolored roofs contrasting sharply with the endless brown, green, and blue of the steppe. The paved roads were mediocre by American standards, but to us they felt like silk. Our English and Northern Irish friends were on a tighter schedule and decided to press on that night, while we stayed in Altai with our Danish and Israeli friends to wait on repairs for the Fiat and treat ourselves to a hot meal, cold beer, bed, and toilet. 

The next morning we all met up back at the repair place, where an apparently drunk mechanic, cigarette in mouth and no eye protection, was busily welding various pieces of metal onto the Danes’ car in an attempt to restore their suspension to a semi-intact state. Around noon, we rolled out of town and spent about 100km on a nice paved road which ended with absolutely no warning just over the crest of a small hill. I wasn’t disappointed, though: save for the washboard stuff, off-roading in Mongolia was the most fun I’ve ever had behind the wheel. With dark clouds building and the wind picking up, Keshav Pothole got its first flat tire of the trip; fortunately, changing a tire is within our extremely limited realm of auto-expertise. Soon after, the storm began in earnest—and with the rain being blown in sheets across the unprotected steppe, the Danes lost their roof rack to an unexpected ridge. The poor guys could not get a break. Three days, three roof racks. 

We made it across hills and valleys covered in bizarre rock formations to a little town where we came upon a Scottish team and a French team who were getting repairs. They joined us at our campsite just past the town, where we had an excellent bonfire with the remains of Rob and Jack’s roof rack, drank brandy, and had a lovely conversation that took full advantage of the myriad nationalities and languages represented by our convoy. Being in convoy with other teams was a crucial part of crossing Mongolia: it’s safer and a hell of a lot more fun. Anybody crazy enough to do the Rally is likely someone you would be happy to spend time with.
The next morning we negotiated a small stream and then made decent time over the endless steppe with only animals for company: confused sheep, curious goats, arrogant camels. The Danes didn’t have to stop for repairs until mid-afternoon, easily a record, and at this point we found ourselves next to a few yurts, one of which had a food sign on it. We walked inside expecting a restaurant of sorts, but it turned out it was just a family’s home: two beds, some chairs, and a central stove that burned cakes of dung. We asked if they could cook us food; they nodded and began showing us different ingredients: carrots, turnips, noodles, a large piece of an unidentified animal. Everything was cut up and thrown into a massive metal bowl on top of the stove with a healthy amount of salt. We drank hot horse milk while waiting, and eventually were treated to a hearty—if rather bland—meal.

We continued our journey. Mongolia is indeed one of the most beautiful countries in the world, but it’s huge and the landscape, though stunning, becomes repetitive. Still, every once in a while we were treated to moments of the sublime, like when we crested a hill with the golden evening light behind us, dark storm clouds in the distance, and a perfect 180-degree rainbow dead ahead. 

That evening, about 20km from Bayankhongor, KP sustained its first relatively serious injury when our rear left suspension spring snapped. We were initially worried, but fortunately our friends reassured us that we would still be able to drive and for the moment it was mainly an issue of comfort. So we said the hell with it and pressed on—the Danes, after all, had been driving without a fully-functioning suspension for days. We camped a few kilometers after Bayankhongor; it was the first campsite in Mongolia from which we could see any signs of habitation. But the stars were still incredible.

We were told that “the fun is over after Bayankhongor,” meaning that from there to Ulaanbaatar the roads are all paved. Turns out this is not entirely the case: there are still stretches of unfinished highway, and the paved roads are mediocre at best (since the roads out of the capital were the first to be built, they’re the oldest in the country). Nevertheless we made good progress and ended our day about 180km from the finish line in UB. Our final night camping was bittersweet: though we looked forward to beds and toilets and real food, we had come to really enjoy sitting around and cooking pasta together under the stars, bundling up against the cold, and crawling in to our sleeping bags at the end of a long day.

That being said, we were close enough that we could taste the finish, and the next day we constantly monitored the odometer as the kilometers ticked slowly by. The roads improved, the land became more developed, and eventually we hit a toll booth. Just after was a most welcome sign: Ulaanbaatar. We made our way to the “graveyard,” from where the cars will be shipped back to Europe, and blasted music while we drove up onto the finish line platform and climbed out of the car for some celebratory photos, followed by the Israelis and, incredibly, the Danes in their embattled Fiat. 

We were ecstatic, but it felt surreal at the same time: we had been planning this trip for over a year, and we’d been on the road for nearly six weeks through an extraordinary succession of different places and cultures. Remarkably, our little car had taken us all this way with hardly any problems. And here we were, suddenly finished, packing up our gear and driving away in a taxi, never to see our beloved KP again. Hopefully, of course, we will eventually see the real Keshav Poddar again once he has finished saving India from various diseases, pollution, corruption, and heat, but his close relative Keshav Pothole is destined for Lithuania, where it will be sold for charity.

Our taxi took us to the Office Hotel in central Ulaanbaatar. Its slogan: “Help Your Business.” Well, the Rally was certainly helping its business, as the Adventurists have turned it into the finish line headquarters. Most of the finishing Ralliers stay here, and there is a big lobby full of velvet chairs where you can eat and drink beer and trade stories from the road. Teams can write their names on a huge board in the order that they finished (in case you’re curious, we filled the esteemed #154 spot) so throughout the day you can have a look to see who else has come in. We’ve gotten to reconnect with the majority of teams we spent time with on the road, which has been wonderful. And the city itself—despite being the coldest and most polluted national capital in the world—has been very enjoyable. Decent Western food abounds, and I have spent my days eating eggs and bacon, drinking coffee, eating more bacon, reading and writing. Cooper ate steak for three consecutive meals. And Nick, before flying off this morning, reveled in the abundant free wifi. It’s a very cheap city too: I got an hour-long massage the other day for $19. Cooper followed suit this afternoon. All in all, UB has provided excellent closure to an incredible experience.

The Mongol Rally truly is an amazing thing to do, and I’ll admit to being a little surprised—as I’m sure some of you probably are—that we managed to complete it. While on the road I had always been a bit anxious in the back of my mind and therefore expected to be thrilled when it was over, which I was. But there was also a twinge of sadness and already part of me feels nostalgic for the open road. When you fly, you’re sort of like a gopher: popping up in a new place with no sense of what lies in between. Traveling by car may not be the most efficient method, but it allows you to see everything along the way, which we often found to be more interesting and rewarding than the destination itself. We hope you’ve enjoyed the blog, and that it’s helped to give you a sense of the Great In-Between. Thanks again for all of your support—we truly couldn’t have done this without you.

Cheers,
The Rubikhans

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/IMG_1192-2.jpg" alt="IMG_1192-2" width="1200" height="800" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1644" />Tumbling across the steppe

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8241908.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1647" />Racing a herd of wild horses (they won)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/IMG_1215-2.jpg" alt="IMG_1215-2" width="1200" height="800" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1645" />Benjie enjoys some fresh air

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8251923.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1649" />The Danes' Fiat, under the torch in Altai

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8241917.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1648" />The Rubikhans pause for a quick team photo

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8251928.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1651" />Nick changes our one and only puncture (while Benjie and Cooper look on and drink beer)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/G0550528-2.jpg" alt="DCIM101GOPRO" width="1200" height="661" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1642" />Our convoy, viewed from above. (Photo courtesy of Benjie's drone/GoPro setup!)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/G0540504-2.jpg" alt="DCIM101GOPRO" width="1200" height="661" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1641" />KP passes a yurt (another drone shot)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8251932.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1652" />Dark storm clouds loom overhead...

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8251935.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1653" />Producing this marvellous light display

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/DSC_0085.jpg" alt="DSC_0085" width="1200" height="798" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1660" />And this rainbow

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8261958.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1655" />One of many livestock crossings

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8261962.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1656" />KP flies by with Benjie at the helm

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8261980.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1657" />"Enjoying" warm horse milk in a yurt

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8272006.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1659" />Our new roofbox, replete with one of our super handy <a href="http://www.goalzero.com/" target="_blank">Goal Zero</a> solar panels (and our power pack inside Cooper's bag)

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8272018.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1662" />Benjie and Adi (one of the Israelis) show off a last-minute cosmetic addition to the car

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/IMG_1321-2.jpg" alt="IMG_1321-2" width="1200" height="800" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1646" />We made it!

<img src="http://crossingtherubikhan.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/P8282070.jpg" alt="OLYMPUS DIGITAL CAMERA" width="1200" height="900" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1663" />Final country beers! It's been a wild ride.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1636</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-08-31 05:20:30</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-08-31 10:20:30</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>mongolia-part-ii</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>3989</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Patty]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>Pattyscheid@yshoo.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.105.251.63</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-31 06:55:07</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-31 11:55:07</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Congratulations, guys! Your blog has been a joy to read.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1409486129.2333209514617919921875;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>3999</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Howard Baetjer]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>hbaetjer@verizon.net</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://hbaetjer@verizon.net</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>108.12.160.53</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-08-31 18:30:06</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-08-31 23:30:06</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Dear Rubikhans, Benjie's Uncle Hojay here. I belatedly discovered yesterday that I can respond to you. Shoot, I would have been commenting quickly to thank you for the indescribably marvelous photos and the delightful account of your journey. Better late than never, though, THANK YOU for the wonderful account, which I have been following with great pleasure. And CONGRATULATIONS on making the whole journey, and on carrying it off with such elan. Please keep the site up so we can all enjoy it for many years to come. Best wishes for safe journeys home, or to Uzbekistan, or wherever you are headed. Well done, guys.
Hojay]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[false]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1409527806.446979045867919921875;s:7:"message";s:28:"Akismet cleared this comment";s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:0:"";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
			<wp:commentmeta>
				<wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
				<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:4:{s:4:"time";d:1428586165.539577960968017578125;s:7:"message";s:47:"buzkashi changed the comment status to approved";s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:8:"buzkashi";}]]></wp:meta_value>
			</wp:commentmeta>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
