<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-03-04T17:24:46-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Crossing the Rubikhan</title><subtitle>Mongol Rally 2014</subtitle><entry><title>Captain’s Log: February Doldrums Lead to March Madness</title><link href="/captains-log/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Captain&#39;s Log: February Doldrums Lead to March Madness" /><published>2014-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/captains-log</id><content type="html" xml:base="/captains-log/">&lt;p&gt;What’s up RubikhanArtists?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather remains unforgivably cold in Hanover (negative 8°F next week? In March?) and Team Crossing the Rubikhan is dreaming of 96-degree days on the M37 highway between Turkmenbashi and Ashgabat. While waiting to receive our second passports—just in case the rogue border patrolman is less than pumped about the two Israeli stamps I have on page 7—we’ve begun to prepare the rest of our applications for visas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who are unfamiliar with the process, applying for one visa can be a bureaucratic nightmare. We need six each—and that includes Russia: The Visa To End All Visas. This means we need to confirm hostel bookings, procure our international driver’s licenses, fill out mounds of paperwork, and somehow convince a series of questionably run government agencies that driving a beat up old car from the UK to Mongolia is a perfectly legitimate and not-at-all-sketchy reason to gain ingress into their esteemed nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooper is going bald trying to keep the rest of us on top of our responsibilities while other serious obligations like schoolwork and Sporcle fight for our extremely limited attention (thanks, technology!). The team is hoping for a miracle tomorrow when the four of us make the quick jaunt to Montpelier to get our international driver’s licenses. There have been murmurs from Benjie that preparing for a certain fraternity formal may get in the way. We get it, Benjie—you have a hot date. You’re still coming. Pics to follow (of the Montpelier trip, not of Benjie’s hot date). Maybe this will be the first installment of &lt;a href=&quot;http://tripwing.com/&quot;&gt;Tripwing&lt;/a&gt;’s highly anticipated #SideMirrorSaturday?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all we’ve got for now. Like always, thanks a ton to all of our incredible donors and sponsors! Special shout-out to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goalzero.com/&quot;&gt;GoalZero&lt;/a&gt; for sending us some amazing solar-powered gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/crossingtherubikhan-blog/images/DSC_0004-1024x680.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_0004-1024x680.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/crossingtherubikhan-blog/images/DSC_0009-1024x680.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_0009-1024x680.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, hello to all the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tripwing.com/&quot;&gt;Tripwingers&lt;/a&gt; out there! If you feel like throwing us a bone, take a gander at our &lt;a href=&quot;http://crossingtherubikhan.com/donate/&quot;&gt;ridiculous rewards packages&lt;/a&gt; and perhaps even donate a shekel or three &lt;a href=&quot;http://crossingtherubikhan.com/donate/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick and Team Crossing the Rubikhan&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>What’s up RubikhanArtists?</summary></entry><entry><title>A Culture A Day</title><link href="/a-culture-a-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Culture A Day" /><published>2014-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/a-culture-a-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="/a-culture-a-day/">&lt;p&gt;Hello Friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re pumped to announce our new partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tripwing.com/&quot;&gt;TripWing&lt;/a&gt;—a travel itinerary booking website that books entire tours along with the standard flight and hotel reservations. While they probably can’t help us pitch a tent in the Turkmen desert, they can do pretty much everything else travel related. Check out everything TripWing can do by visiting &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tripwing.com/&quot;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;. Oh yeah, and feel free to check out our &lt;a href=&quot;http://crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate&quot;&gt;donations page&lt;/a&gt; too….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time, here’s a list of weird cultural idiosyncrasies we’re likely to encounter on our drive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;obscure-customs-well-inevitably-break-along-the-way&quot;&gt;Obscure Customs We’ll Inevitably Break Along the Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turkey&lt;/strong&gt;: Holding your thumb between your index and middle finger is the equivalent of flipping the bird and to be avoided at all costs. While not verified by any reputable source, this likely stems from too many lost noses in the “Got Your Nose!” disaster of 1963.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azerbaijan&lt;/strong&gt;: If you meet a person with empty buckets, you are bound for misfortune. Cast down your bucket where you are!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uzbekistan&lt;/strong&gt;: Refilling a guest’s teacup that is more than half-full is a rude way of saying that you want them to leave. After three smelly weeks packed into a tiny car, this technique may be abetted by good old-fashioned passive aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Georgia&lt;/strong&gt;: Bring an odd number of flowers, as even numbers are used in funerals. This means that when Benjie buys a dozen roses from the Tbilisi florist, he can give 11 to his crush and still have one left over for his ego.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kyrgyzstan&lt;/strong&gt;: If a bottle of vodka is opened, it must be finished in one sitting. Good luck, Keshav.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kazakhstan&lt;/strong&gt;: A boiled sheep’s head is sometimes presented on a beautiful plate to the most honored guest, who then symbolically serves sections of the head among the guests. The daughter-in-law and host’s daughter are given sections of the tongue as a reminder to ‘hold their tongues.’ Cooper will presumably be given the teeth as a reminder to brush his teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Russia&lt;/strong&gt;: Do not bring yellow flowers; it is a sign of cheating on love. I don’t know why these etiquette websites are so obsessed with flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uzbekistan&lt;/strong&gt;: Partially because unemployment is rampant, people generally have a lot of free time. There is no set bus schedule: buses generally just run whenever they fill up/feel like it. Translation: if our car breaks down in Uzbekistan, we’d better not be in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mongolia&lt;/strong&gt;: If you accidentally tap someone’s foot with your own, immediately shake hands with him. Since Mongolia is the most sparsely populated country in the world, I can’t imagine this has ever happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turkmenistan&lt;/strong&gt;: Narrowly beating out Justin Bieber as the most bizarre cult of personality this side of North Korea, Turkmenistan’s former President For Life, Saparmurat Niyazov is one crazy individual. He renamed himself Turkmenbashi, meaning “Father of all Turkmen” and subsequently renamed several cities, towns, streets, and the month of January after himself. There is a 50ft tall golden statue of him in the capital that rotates so as to always face the sun. While Turkmenbashi died in 2006, a book promulgating his glory,written by none other than Turkmenbashi himself, is still taught in all Turkmen schools. My guess would be to avoid making fun of this dude until we hit the Uzbek border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;3 Nick&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Hello Friends!</summary></entry><entry><title>Happy New Year</title><link href="/happy-new-year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy New Year" /><published>2013-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/happy-new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="/happy-new-year/">&lt;p&gt;It’s 2014 in Mongolia!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beloved friends, family, and people who read obscure blogs for fun: I wanted to take a few minutes to update you on our preparations—at least those outside of calculating carbon footprints and monkey mischief quotients. In the midst of our holiday break, Cooper, Benjie, Keshav, and I have struck a delicate balance between Rally preparations, sleeping, and catching up on Homeland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of finding generous sponsors and watching Cooper build us a beautiful interactive map, we’ve allowed ourselves to dive into the nitty gritty of day to day equipment needs (sample: 4 headlamps, 2 walkie talkies, 1 car).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve nailed down the hilariously bureaucratic means through which we will secure our visas. I’ll double check with Keshav but I think Turkmenistan requires $40 cash and a floral offering from the eldest member of our village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve reached out for advice wherever we can get it. Thanks to everyone for the invaluable recommendations regarding everything from bribes to brakepads. A couple of favorite pieces of advice have been to chat up that locals as much as we can and to politely refuse offerings of snuff by sniffing it and finding a way to adequately pantomime ‘no thank you.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have our work cut out for us with seven months until we launch in London. Our biggest tasks include acquiring a car, learning how to drive it, and learning how to fix it. Piece of cake, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I sign off, I want to say a huge thanks to all who have donated! We cannot properly express just how much it means that you’re supporting our causes as well as our dream of adventure. Also, shout out to &lt;a href=&quot;http://bigfrog.com/pdx&quot;&gt;Big Frog Custom T-Shirts&lt;/a&gt; in Portland for printing up some great looking t-shirts (look out for ‘em on campus this winter!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you’re feeling in the holiday spirit and want to fund a fan belt or our passage across the Caspian, I encourage you to visit our &lt;a href=&quot;http://crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate&quot;&gt;donations page&lt;/a&gt; and check out the wonderfully weird rewards packages we’ll give you in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hobey Ho, let’s go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;//Nick&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>It’s 2014 in Mongolia!</summary></entry><entry><title>Cars and Carbon Consciousness</title><link href="/cars-and-carbon-consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cars and Carbon Consciousness" /><published>2013-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/cars-and-carbon-consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/cars-and-carbon-consciousness/">&lt;p&gt;Greetings, good readers, and welcome to the first (well, second) installment in our ongoing Mongol Rally chronicles! Although our July 19th start date is still several months away, we are already in the midst of planning. And by that, we really just mean ogling photo essays of Mongolia, practicing throat singing, and getting a head start on the obligatory Mongol Rally muttonchops (not really). We’ll do our very best to keep you abreast of our planning efforts as we continue to prepare for the 10,000-mile adventure that lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post addresses a question that a number of you have raised, and one that we believe merits a blog entry of its own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Isn’t driving 10,000 miles sort of antithetical to the Cool Earth Foundation’s whole ‘save the rainforest and reduce greenhouse gases’ mission?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our answer? On paper, yes – driving 10,000 miles is not good for the environment, and we won’t pretend like it is. In reality, however, the emissions we will produce over the course of our journey pale in comparison to the emissions we’ll prevent from entering the atmosphere by donating to Cool Earth. Bear with me, as I attempt to illustrate this comparison using real figures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Cool Earth, £60 – a hair under $100USD, at the time of writing – protects one acre of rainforest. So, if we donate $1,500 to Cool Earth (that’s half of our total fundraising amount, with the other half going to SOS Children’s Villages), we’ll presumably protect 15 acres of rainforest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, clearing one acre of rainforest emits 260 tonnes of CO2 into the atmosphere. (Of course, it also displaces countless monkeys, tapirs, and anacondas). So, if we can protect 15 acres of forest, we’ll effectively keep 3,900 tonnes of CO2 safely out of the atmosphere. Meanwhile, those trees on the ground will continue to belch out the oxygen we so dearly need, while the monkeys inhabiting them will go about their daily mischief-making uninterrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving along, consider that 260 tonnes of CO2 – again, the amount produced by one acre of deforestation – is roughly equivalent to driving an average petrol-powered vehicle around the globe…a staggering 32 times! And the 3,900 tonnes of CO2 that our donation will help keep out of the atmosphere? That equals something like 480 laps around the planet! See where I’m going with this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these numbers are correct, then one planetary lap produces something like 8.125 tonnes of CO2. We’re driving approximately 10,000 miles, or a little less than halfway around the planet. So while we’re certainly guilty of producing our own greenhouse gases – approximately 3.26 tonnes, if we assume that the circumference of the planet is 24,901 miles (as our good friend Google seems to indicate) and that our odometer hits the 10,000 mark – WE ARE STILL KEEPING AROUND 3,896 tonnes of CO2 SAFELY OUT OF THE ATMOSPHERE! And that, I think, is something we can all be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as these hasty calculations hopefully illustrate, our little jaunt to Mongolia isn’t quite so environmentally harmful as it may initially seem, in the grand scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, today we hit our charity fundraising goal of $3,000 – hooray! While this is an exciting milestone, however, we still need your support in order to make this trip a reality. So, if you’ve got any coins rattling around in your pockets (err, Paypal account), or just want to help four young lads realize a dream, head on over to our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crossingtherubikhan.com/#donate&quot;&gt;donation page&lt;/a&gt;. The rewards packages we’ve prepared for you – not to mention our forthcoming updates from the road – will ensure that you won’t regret it. If anything, do it for the monkeys and the tapirs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, stay tuned for more blog posts in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;//Cooper&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Greetings, good readers, and welcome to the first (well, second) installment in our ongoing Mongol Rally chronicles! Although our July 19th start date is still several months away, we are already in the midst of planning. And by that, we really just mean ogling photo essays of Mongolia, practicing throat singing, and getting a head start on the obligatory Mongol Rally muttonchops (not really). We’ll do our very best to keep you abreast of our planning efforts as we continue to prepare for the 10,000-mile adventure that lies ahead.</summary></entry><entry><title>Hello There!</title><link href="/hello-there/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello There!" /><published>2013-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/hello-there</id><content type="html" xml:base="/hello-there/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks for visiting our blog. We’ll be using this space to keep everyone informed on how our preparations are progressing, and of course how the drive is going once the rally actually begins. But that’s still pretty far off; for now, we need to deal with some basic necessities. Like a car! If you’d like to help us out in that department, head on down to the “Get Involved” section of the website, where you can conveniently donate through PayPal. Remember that the majority of your donation will go to help keep the earth cool and shelter orphaned children, two causes I think we can all agree are very worthwhile. So please consider supporting us!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Thanks for visiting our blog. We’ll be using this space to keep everyone informed on how our preparations are progressing, and of course how the drive is going once the rally actually begins. But that’s still pretty far off; for now, we need to deal with some basic necessities. Like a car! If you’d like to help us out in that department, head on down to the “Get Involved” section of the website, where you can conveniently donate through PayPal. Remember that the majority of your donation will go to help keep the earth cool and shelter orphaned children, two causes I think we can all agree are very worthwhile. So please consider supporting us!</summary></entry></feed>
